<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Speculum Britanniae. The first parte an historicall, &amp; chorographicall discription of Middlesex. Wherin are also alphabeticallie sett downe, the names of the cyties, townes, parishes hamletes, howses of name &amp;c. W.th direction spedelie to finde anie place desired in the mappe &amp; the distance betwene place and place without compasses. Cum priuilegio. By the trauaile and vew of Iohn Norden. Anno 1593</title>
            <title>Speculum Britanniae. Part 1</title>
            <author>Norden, John, 1548-1625?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1593</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08306</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113229</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848466</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848466</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13561</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08306)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13561)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 326:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Speculum Britanniae. The first parte an historicall, &amp; chorographicall discription of Middlesex. Wherin are also alphabeticallie sett downe, the names of the cyties, townes, parishes hamletes, howses of name &amp;c. W.th direction spedelie to finde anie place desired in the mappe &amp; the distance betwene place and place without compasses. Cum priuilegio. By the trauaile and vew of Iohn Norden. Anno 1593</title>
                  <title>Speculum Britanniae. Part 1</title>
                  <author>Norden, John, 1548-1625?</author>
                  <author>Keere, Pieter van den, ca. 1571-ca. 1624, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 48, [4] p., [3] folded plates : maps, coats of arms (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Eliot's Court Press,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1593]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The title page is engraved and signed "Pieter Vanden Keere scalp: [sic] 1593." Variant 1: title page unsigned.</note>
                  <note>Identification of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>With Elizabeth I's arms on [A]2v. Variant 2: this page blank.</note>
                  <note>With an Anglo-Saxon alphabet on [A]4v. Variant 3: quire [A] in another, probably earlier setting, lacking the alphabet.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Middlesex I. pars Speculi Britanniæ.</note>
                  <note>With a final leaf of verses and errata.</note>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Both CSmH 62784 and CSmH 62786 are filmed.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Middlesex (England) --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>engraved title page</figDesc>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
                  </figure>
                  <p>SPECVLVM BRITANNIAE.</p>
                  <p>The firſt parte</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An hiſtoricall, &amp; chorographicall diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</hi> Middleſex. <hi>Wherin are alſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabeticallie ſett downe, the names of the cyties, townes, pariſhes hamletes, howſes of name &amp;c. W<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. direction ſpedelie to finde anie place deſired in the mappe &amp; the diſtance betwene place and place Without compaſses.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CVM PRIVILEGIO</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>BY <hi>THE TRAVAILE AND VEW</hi> OF Iohn Norden <hi>Anno</hi> 1593</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:2"/>
            <p>TO THE HIGH, AND MOST MIGHTY EMPRES, ELIZABETH, BY THE DIVINE PROVIDENCE, QVEENE OF ENGLAND, FRAVNCE, AND IRELAND, POWERFVL PROTEC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TOR OF THE FAITH, AND VNDOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TED RELIGION OF THE MES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIAH, THE MOST COMFORTABLE NVRSING MOTHER OF THE ISRAEL OF GOD, IN THE BRITISH ISLES.</p>
            <p>HER HIGHNES LOYALL SVBIECT IOHN NORDEN, IN ALL HV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MILITIE, CONSECRATETH HIS SPECVLVM BRITANNIAE.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>E R</head>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <q>SEMPER EADEM</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE SIR WILLIAM CECILL KNIGHT, LORDE BVRGHLEY, <hi>Lordhigh Treaſurer of England,</hi> and of hir Maieſties moſt <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable priuy Counſell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing by your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable meane (my good Lord) obtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, at the hands of my ſacred SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REIGNE, gratious paſſe, &amp; priuiledge, for mine intended labours, the deſcription of famous ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND. I cannot but, in dutie, render vnto your Honor, condigne thanks, and withall diligence, and dutifull endeuour, proceed therein: hoping, that although (in regarde of my long ſicknes &amp; other impediments) this beginning carrie not ſo abſolute per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as in your wiſedome may be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: yet may I enioy your patient directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and gratious aſſiſtance, I ſhall effect the reſidue more fully to anſwere Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable expectation.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors in all dutie, <hi>IO. NORDEN</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:4"/>
            <head>TO THE CONSIDERATION OF THE HONORABLE, WISE, AND LEARNED.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I cannot but confeſſe that I am the vnwoorthieſt of manie in this lande, (and eſpeciallie in theſe daies of ſurpaſſing knowledge) to vndertake (after other farre more deſeruing) ſo commendable a labor: which requireth arte, induſtrie, learning, counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and charge, wherewith I am not ſo fullie fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed as ſome other. Yet it may pleaſe you (in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour) to accept of my willingnes, and beare with my wants: And the rather for that it hath beene helde heeretofore an excuſe (in curteſie) <hi>Velle bene,</hi> though in this age (more ripe in experience) is expected, <hi>Optimè perficere:</hi> which neither, altogither eſcapeth without emulation: I, as ouercome with a deſire to take pains to profite my Countrey, reſt vndoubtfull, that the wiſe, and learned, will not onely tollerate, but in fauour accept this ſimple beginning.</p>
            <p>The fruits of my trauell tend not alone to my ſelfe in priuate, but to the publike eaſe of many. In lieu whereof, my hope and deſire is, that he that can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue, will friendly reforme what he findeth iuſtly faultie. So ſhall my proceedings grow to more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: and I by all endeuour will ſeeke to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh what may anſwere diſcret affections.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Nihil vbique placet.</hi> IO. NORDEN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:4"/>
            <head>Aduertiſements touching the vſe of this labor.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is to be noted, that for your eaſe I haue in the list of the Map of the Shire, ſet downe certaine deuiſions, letters, and figures: the deuiſions are in ſteed of a ſcale of the miles, the leſſer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining one, the greater two miles. The letters and figures ſerue for the preſent finding of any place deſired in the Map, which places are found in the Alphabet with the letter and figure that direct to the place deſired. A matter of ſo great facilitie as needeth no example.</p>
            <p>He that deſireth to know the distance betweene places in the Map without compaſſes, the vſe of the croſſing lines, which ſerue for a vniuerſall ſcale through the Map, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his deſire.</p>
            <p>Whereas in the collection of the Alphabeticall table, there are heere and there diſperſed houſes of Nobility &amp; Gentrie. I craue fauorable conſideration, though I haue not ſo narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acquired their interestes, as that may aſſure me, that they be all the true ownoures in fee, of the places which they are reſident in, which thing to obſerue; as it doth not meerely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine to my purpoſe, So were it a matter intricate, and the more, for that information (often vncertaine) muſt be of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, the chiefeſt guide therein. Such therefore as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue moſt doubtfull for want of certaine certificat, I haue noted with two ſtarres thus, **.</p>
            <p>Alſo in this commencement of my trauailes, I haue obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued certain funeral monuments with the armes (if any ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reſt vndefaced) which if it may be fauorably conceiued, I ſhall with more diligence obſerue the like hereafter, whereby may be preſerued in perpetuall memory, that which time may deface, and ſwallow vp in obliuion. Alſo by this obſeruation, many may be certified of the places where their aunceſtors and allies are interred, and by the coates finde out their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne kinred.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Negotium ex negotio ſeritur. <hi>IOHN NORDEN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:5"/>
            <head>Io. Nordenivale, ad primam par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſui SPECVLI BRITANNIAE.</head>
            <l>VAde liber <hi>Speculi</hi> caput es, tua me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra ſequentur,</l>
            <l>ELISABETHA potens, arx<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> patrona tua eſt.</l>
            <l>Quid ſi in te domin úm<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> tuum ruet inuidus audax?</l>
            <l>Tu dominúſque tuus, tutus inermis eris.</l>
            <l>Ito foràs, valeáſque liber, te forte ſagaces</l>
            <l>Incultum voluant: caetera culta forent,</l>
            <l>Ibis in orbe gerens, quamuis tua fata libelle,</l>
            <l>Ardua principio, ſpes meliora canit.</l>
            <l>ELISABETHA valens, altiſſima, maxima, firma,</l>
            <l>Auxilium, quandò, ſceua procella venit.</l>
            <l>Haec tibi conductum, non te pericula tangunt,</l>
            <l>Digna patrona illa eſt, ſpeſque, ſaluſque tua.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="alphabet">
            <head>The Saxon Alphabet.</head>
            <p>A b c d E f g H i k l M n o p q r S s t u ƿ X x y</p>
            <p>
               <hi>a</hi>
               <seg rend="above">A</seg> 
               <hi>b</hi>
               <seg rend="above">b</seg> 
               <hi>c</hi>
               <seg rend="above">c</seg> 
               <hi>d</hi>
               <seg rend="above">d</seg> 
               <hi>e</hi>
               <seg rend="above">e</seg> 
               <hi>f</hi>
               <seg rend="above">f</seg> 
               <hi>g</hi>
               <seg rend="above">g</seg> 
               <hi>h</hi>
               <seg rend="above">h</seg> 
               <hi>i</hi>
               <seg rend="above">i</seg> 
               <hi>k</hi>
               <seg rend="above">k</seg> 
               <hi>l</hi>
               <seg rend="above">l</seg> 
               <hi>m</hi>
               <seg rend="above">m</seg> 
               <hi>n</hi>
               <seg rend="above">n</seg> 
               <hi>o</hi>
               <seg rend="above">o</seg> 
               <hi>p</hi>
               <seg rend="above">p</seg> 
               <hi>q</hi>
               <seg rend="above">q</seg> 
               <hi>r</hi>
               <seg rend="above">r</seg> 
               <hi>S</hi>
               <seg rend="above">S</seg> 
               <hi>s</hi>
               <seg rend="above">s</seg> 
               <hi>t</hi>
               <seg rend="above">t</seg> 
               <hi>u</hi>
               <seg rend="above">u</seg> 
               <hi>w</hi>
               <seg rend="above">w</seg> 
               <hi>X</hi>
               <seg rend="above">X</seg> 
               <hi>x</hi>
               <seg rend="above">x</seg> 
               <hi>y</hi>
               <seg rend="above">y</seg>
            </p>
            <p>AE<seg rend="above">Æ</seg> 
               <hi>ae</hi>
               <seg rend="above">æ</seg> 
               <hi>Th</hi>
               <seg rend="above">Ð</seg> 
               <hi>th</hi>
               <seg rend="above">ð</seg> 
               <hi>th</hi>
               <seg rend="above">þ</seg> 
               <hi>and</hi>
               <seg rend="above">&amp;</seg> 
               <hi>that</hi>
               <seg rend="above">ꝧ</seg>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13561:5"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE DECLARATION OF THE TITLES, INHABITANTS, DIVISIONS, AND SCITVATION OF <hi>ENGLAND</hi> or <hi>BRITANNIA</hi> maior: a neceſſary introduction to our <hi>Speculum Britanniae.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Otwithſtanding it reſteth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, how, when, and by whom, this our BRITAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIA was firſt peopled, yet to ſatisfie ſuch as expect the iudgements, and opinions of ſome auncient writers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame:<note place="margin">Beroſus <hi>in Chald. ant. Annius in</hi> Beroſ. Caeſar. Com.</note> I thinke it not impertinent to ſcite the affirmation of<note n="*" place="margin">Some ſuſpect that the hiſtorie of <hi>Beroſus,</hi> was but counterfeit, falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathered vpon hu name, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore helde of no great authoritie.</note> 
               <hi>Beroſus,</hi> who ſaith that <hi>Samothes</hi> called alſo <hi>Meſech,</hi> brother to <hi>Gomer</hi> and <hi>Tuball,</hi> called alſo <hi>Dis,</hi> the ſixt ſonne of <hi>Iaphet,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Noah,</hi> came into this land about 252. yeres after the floud: who called it <hi>Samothea,</hi> 3593. yeeres paſt: in which name it continued vntill <hi>Albion,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Neptune,</hi> (who diſcended of <hi>Cham</hi>) entred the ſame, and chaunged the name of <hi>Samothea</hi> into ALBION. This <hi>Albìon</hi> raigned about 562.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ringman.</hi> in deſ Europae.</note> yeeres after the floud: in the yeere of the worlds creation 2219. 3340. yeeres ſince. <hi>Plinie</hi> calleth it ALVION. <hi>Ptolomey</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Strabo Munster,</hi> and others,<note place="margin">Munſt. <hi>Coſm.</hi>
               </note> will haue it ALBION <hi>ab albis rupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> of the white ſea clifes, which are in the ſouth coaſt of the lande:</p>
            <p>Some others will haue it come of the Greeke worde <hi>Olbion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Olbion. Cowp. <hi>in Dict.</hi>
               </note> which ſignifieth <hi>felix</hi> happie, in regarde of their happines belike that firſt atchiued it. So doth <hi>Strabo</hi> call <hi>Albania,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Strabo <hi>lib.</hi> 4.</note> wherein he pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the people <hi>Caucaſiae: felicem habitatu regionem,</hi> a happie coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie to dwell in. So is <hi>Gothia</hi> in the countrey language <hi>ierra bona,</hi> a good countrey. Some will haue it ALBION of <hi>Albina Diocle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> daughter, which hath no próbabilitie.<note place="margin">Caxton.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It continued in the name of ALBION 608. yeeres, vntill <hi>Bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> or <hi>Brutus Iulius,</hi> arriuall, who conquered the ſame about the yeere of the worldes creation 2828. 2734.<note place="margin">Brutes <hi>arriuall.</hi> Galf. Monum. Bale <hi>Cent.</hi> 1.</note> This <hi>Brute</hi> changed the name of ALBION into BRYTANE, and the people <hi>Albionds</hi> into <hi>Britans;</hi> or after ſome BRVTAYNE of the ſame <hi>Brute <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> being turned into v.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:13561:6"/>Some will haue it BRITANNIA of <hi>Brytona</hi> a nymph of Greece:<note place="margin">Britanniae.</note> others rather holde that it ſhoulde take that name of a ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as M.<note place="margin">Twinus <hi>in Com.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Twine</hi> in his Commentaries, who ſaith, <hi>Britannia</hi> is ſo called, for that it is <hi>Locus diuorſio ſeparatus ab eo cui adhaeſerat:</hi> a place ſeuered from another whereunto it was annexed: and the more to fortifie his reaſon, he coniectureth that this <hi>Britannia</hi> (nowe an apparant Iſland) was ſomtime <hi>Peninſula</hi> annexed vnto the maine of Fraunce; which no doubt is true, but not ſince the generall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation, (by probabilitie) whereby infinite chanels were eaten in the earth, with the rage of ſo violent a floud, and conſequently many Iſlands diſperſed as we ſee in the main Ocean, and middle earth ſeas: for ſurely if it had beene <hi>Peninſula,</hi> or <hi>Istmus</hi> ſince the floud,<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> 
               <hi>Plinie</hi> who liued neere 1500. yeeres before M. <hi>Twyne</hi> woulde haue as well mentioned ſuch a conjunction, as that part of the ſea which runneth betweene England and Calleys, which he calleth <hi>Mare Geſſoriacum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mare Geſſoriacu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> and which <hi>Ptolomey</hi> calleth <hi>Oceanus Britannicus.</hi> But it ſeemeth that M. <hi>Twyne</hi> ſtandeth vpon the opinion of <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Volſcus</hi> a Poet, who dreameth of a paſſage fiue miles in bredth betweene England and Fraunce: from whom alſo <hi>Seruius Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> ſeemeth to ſay,<note place="margin">Seruius Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</note> that BRITANNIA was <hi>Olim iuncta continenti,</hi> our <hi>Brytaine</hi> was ioined to the maine continent: which ſecrets paſſe our apprehenſion.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Eliot</hi> will haue <hi>Britannia</hi> to be <hi>Pritania: Humfrey Lloyd</hi> alſo ſeemeth to ſay it ſhould be <hi>Prid-caine</hi> which ſignifieth beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or white of colour,<note place="margin">S. Th. Eliot. Humf. Lloyde.</note> though the <hi>c</hi> be omitted for more eaſier pronunciation, which maketh it <hi>Pridaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, ſome will haue it come of <hi>Brith</hi> a britiſh worde, which ſignifieth painted, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iecture I take to come of <hi>Caeſars</hi> words, where he ſaith,<note place="margin">Caeſar <hi>Com. lib.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Omnes Britanni glasto ſe inficiunt,</hi> all the Brytons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmere themſelues, and ſtaine their bodies with oade: of which worde <hi>Brith</hi> and <hi>tania</hi> a Greeke worde which ſignifieth <hi>Regnum</hi> a kingdome, it is ſuppoſed to be aptly called <hi>Brithtania,</hi> the countrey or kingdome of the <hi>Brithtons</hi> or depainted people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goropius Becanus</hi> ſeemeth to hold another opinion, that it ſhould be <hi>Bridania,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Goropius Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus. M. Camden.</note> wherof M. <hi>Camden</hi> maketh conſtruction, that <hi>Bri</hi> in <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dania</hi> ſhould be free, and ſo to make it <hi>Fredania,</hi> or <hi>Free-denmarke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus is our <hi>Britannia</hi> forced to ſuſtaine ſundry titles vnder one truth,<note place="margin">The ſeuerall titles of Brytaine.</note> as <hi>Brytannia, Pritania, Prid-caine</hi> or <hi>Pridayne, Brithtania, Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tania, Bridania,</hi> and ſuch like: according to as manie ſundrie mens conceits. But were not <hi>Brute</hi> ſo generally reiected in theſe our daies, I could verie eaſely be drawne to aſſure me that it might be moſt truely <hi>Brutania</hi> of <hi>Brute</hi> the ſuppoſed conquerour, and that Greeke worde <hi>tania</hi> a kingdome, though <hi>Brute</hi> were no Greeke, yet might he fitly conioyne this worde <hi>tania</hi> vnto his name <hi>Brute,</hi> and ſo conclude it <hi>Brutania,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Brutania.</note> 
               <hi>Bruti regnum,</hi> the kingdome of <hi>Brute,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13561:6"/>u</hi> being nowe turned into <hi>i,</hi> as in other wordes, <hi>Peſſumus</hi> is nowe written <hi>Peſſimus,</hi> ſo are manie other Latine words. Manie of late yeeres reiect the hyſtorie of <hi>Brute,</hi> among others, an Abbot ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time of S. Albons, <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Wheathamſted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io. <hi>de</hi> Wheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampſt.</note> who wrote about the yere of Chriſt, 1443. who ſaith plainly, that <hi>Totus proceſſus de Bruto illo, eſt Poeticus, potius quam historicus:</hi> The whole matter of that <hi>Brute</hi> is Poeticall, (fabulous) rather than a true hyſtorie. This author liuing of late daies affoordeth reproofe of the moſt auncient. But what antiquitie hath left, and wee by tradition haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, <hi>Ipſe ſciolus,</hi> dare not abſolutelie denie, vppon anie mans bare coniecture.</p>
            <p>It is at this day called ENGLAND, <hi>Anglorum terra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">England.</note> the land of Angles, or Engliſhmen, the Latins call it <hi>Anglia,</hi> and the French <hi>Angle terre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Angli or Engliſhmen inhabited part of Germanie whom (as I take it) <hi>Ptolomey</hi> calleth <hi>Angili:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Angili.</hi> Ptolomey.</note> and placeth them betweene the <hi>Caſuari,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Chemae,</hi> neer the riuer <hi>Viſurgis,</hi> now <hi>Weſer,</hi> in that countrey which is now <hi>Westphalia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caeſ. Com.</note> who (as <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaith) <hi>Praedae ac belli inferendi cauſa, ex Belgis tranſierunt,</hi> came out of <hi>Belgia</hi> the lowe Countries, to ſeeke releefe, and to war with the Britons: inuading moſt eſpecially that part of the lande which borders vppon the ſouth eaſt, or Germaine ſea, as Kent, Suſſex, &amp; Eſſex.<note place="margin">Beda.</note> The <hi>Angles</hi> or Engliſhmen inhabited Cambridgeſhire, Iſle of Elie, Norffolke and Suffolke; all which was called <hi>Eastanglia,</hi> and the people <hi>East Angles,</hi> The Saxons which came alſo with the <hi>Angles</hi> were diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſeated in other quarters of the lande, as by the deuiſion, and Heptarchie it will appeere.</p>
            <p>The Saxons and Angles draue the Britons into Wales,<note place="margin">Aun. dom. <hi>620.</hi>
               </note> and Cornewall, and other places of refuge. And <hi>Egbert</hi> king of the weſt Saxons became ſole Monarch of the whole land, and called the ſame England, of that part of Germany wherof he was, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Angili</hi> or Angles inhabited.</p>
            <p>Some other will haue it England of <hi>Anglia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anglia.</note> the name of a Queene, ſometime of this Countrey. But what, whence, or when ſhe was they ſeeme not to report.</p>
            <p>Others will haue it <hi>Anglia,</hi> ſcytuate as it were in <hi>Angulo</hi> in a corner, or newke by it ſelfe. Which opinion is not altogither to be reiected, for that <hi>Iulius Solinus</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Iulius Solinus.</note> that the ſea coaſt of Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia had beene the ende of the worlde, but that the Iſle of Britaine, (which ſtandeth alone as it were in an angle) for the largenes thereof, deſerueth the name of another worlde, being ſeperated from the reſt of the earth, as <hi>Virgil</hi> ſaith, <hi>Penitus toto diuiſos orbe Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannos. Ioſephus</hi> in the oration of king <hi>Agrippa</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſ.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>26,</hi> bel. Iud.</note> 
               <hi>The Romaines ſought another world, beyond the great Ocean, ſending their hoſtes into Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne.</hi> And <hi>Aegiſpus</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Romaines by ſtrength gat another
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13561:7"/>world beyond the Ocean in Britaine far from them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Allgiſ.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> de excid. Hier. <hi>Ant. Volſc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Antonius Volſcus</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, <hi>Peloponeſum</hi> to be <hi>Vltìmum orbem, Brìtannìam verò alterum or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem:</hi> So that it may be ſaide it ſtandeth in <hi>Angulo,</hi> yet it ſeemeth not thereof to be called <hi>Anglia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This our famous BRITANNIA (of it ſelfe another world) for the firtilitie and pleaſantnes thereof, hath been ſought for, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, and inhabited of many ſundrie nations.</p>
            <p>The firſt as ſome dreame were <hi>Aborigines</hi> ſuch people as the earth it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Aborigines.</note> without humaine propagation brought foorth: who belike followe <hi>Ouid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ouid</hi> metamor.</note> who ſaith, <hi>Caetera diuerſis tellus animalia formis. ſponte ſuo peperit, &amp;c.</hi> But to ſay that men ſhould ſpring of the earth ſince <hi>Adam</hi> diſagreeth from the word of God, whereby we learne that God created them male and female, to increaſe &amp; multiply, &amp; to gouerne all other earthly creatures. There were a people in Italie,<note place="margin">Aborigines in Italie.</note> and they of very great antiquitie: yet not begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten or ſprong of the earth, but becauſe they were <hi>Vagi,</hi> and <hi>Sine la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus,</hi> wanderers vpon the earth without houſe or home, voide of all ciuilitie; &amp; becauſe they were vnknowne from whom they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended, they were accounted <hi>Nullorum filii,</hi> the children of no fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as the Romanes who bluſh not to ſay they are <hi>Deorum filii,</hi> deſcended of the Gods. Such might be in this land at the Britons ariuall;<note place="margin">Giants in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Britons. Ann. mundi <hi>2855</hi> Deut. <hi>1.28.</hi>
               </note> which might bee counted <hi>Indigenae, Vagi,</hi> vnciuill, and therefore called Giants, as were the <hi>Anakimes</hi> mentioned in the Scripture.</p>
            <p>But to leaue theſe vnknowne people;<note place="margin">Yuand. <hi>Do.</hi> Toloſ. <hi>lib. de genel.</hi> Iapheth.</note> 
               <hi>Yuandus</hi> writeth that our <hi>Britannia</hi> was inhabited firſt by Babylonians: But it is not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied that the Britons, (whereof ſoeuer ſo named) were the firſt that vnder ciuill regiment poſſeſſed this land.<note place="margin">Romanes.</note> After them the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, whom <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> firſt conducted hither: &amp; after him <hi>Claudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> the Emperor came into this land with his Romanes about <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Chriſti</hi> 40.<note place="margin">Iulius Caeſar. Claudius <hi>impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. Pictes, Scots.</hi> Beede. <hi>M.</hi> Camden. <hi>Scots afflict the Britons.</hi>
               </note> After the Romanes came the Pictes and Scots out of Scythia (as <hi>Beede</hi> reporteth.) But M. <hi>Camden</hi> taketh them to bee Britons which fled into the north parts for feare of the Romanes. The Scots poſſeſſing the North parts of Britaine, <hi>Albania</hi> nowe Scotland, greatly afflicted the Britons, of the South, who craued aide of the Saxons, and they with the Angles ariuing: in proceſſe of time ſubdued the Britons, and poſſeſſed the lande, driuing the Britons into <hi>Cambria</hi> now Wales, into Cornewall and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of refuge,<note place="margin">Ann. Dom. <hi>1012.</hi> Danes. <hi>William</hi> duke of Normandy with his Normans.</note> about the yeere of Chriſt, 430. Then came the Danes, and diſtreſſed the Saxons neere 200. yeeres. Laſtlie the Normans vnder the conduct of <hi>William</hi> duke of Normandie, who vnder a pretended title ſubiected this lande vnto himſelfe about the yeere of Chriſt 1066. by which conqueſt he is intituled WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM the CONQVEROR, who inforced all the inhabitants to ſweare vnto him fealtie, faith, and true allegeaunce, and being
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13561:7"/>quietlie ſetled in his kingdome, cauſed this land to be deſcribed and exactly ſurueied about the 15. yeere of his raigne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>William Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror</hi> cauſed England to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueied. Doomes day book.</note> wherein he cauſed to be obſerued, how many hides of land, there were in his kingdome, the value of euery hide, and who poſſeſſed it: which ſuruey reſteth in record at Weſtminſter in a booke called <hi>Doomes day,</hi> or the role of <hi>Winchester.</hi> The vſuall account of lande at this day in Englande is by acres, yardes, carewes, hydes, knightes fees, cantreds, baronies and counties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Xiphilinus</hi> diuideth this land into <hi>Britanniam Superiorem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ex <hi>Dione.</hi> England how deuided.</note> &amp; <hi>Inferio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem: Ptolomey</hi> into <hi>Magnam</hi> &amp; <hi>Paruam: Sextus Rufus,</hi> who liued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Emperor <hi>Valentinian,</hi> hath <hi>Britanniam primam,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſecundam flauiam,</hi> and <hi>Maximam Caeſarienſem,</hi> another part added called <hi>Valentia,</hi> remembred by <hi>Marcellinus.</hi> It was alſo deuided into <hi>Loe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gria, Cambria,</hi> and <hi>Albania,</hi> called alſo <hi>Caledonia,</hi> which are nowe <hi>England, Wales,</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was deuided into ſeauen kingdomes by the <hi>Saxons,</hi> after, into Prouinces, Shires or Counties, all which were enhabited by peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of ſeuerall names after <hi>Ptolomey,</hi> as may appeere.</p>
            <list>
               <head>7. king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the SAX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS.</head>
               <item>1. Norþanhym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braric. <hi>regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Northumbroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the kingdome of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumbers.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Northumberland</hi> &amp; part of SCOTLAND.</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Brigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Weſtmerland.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cumberland.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The <hi>Biſh.</hi> of <hi>Durham</hi> or <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelm.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Yorkeſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Lancaſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. Myrcnaric <hi>regnum Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciorum,</hi> the kingdome of Mercia.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Cornaui.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cheſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Shropſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Staffordſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Warwickeſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Worcesterſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Coritani.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Nottinghamſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Lincolneſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Northamptonſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Rutlandſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Leicesterſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Derbiſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Dobuni.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Gloceſterſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Oxfordſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Catticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chlani.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Buckinghamſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Bedfordſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Part of <hi>Hartfordſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Herefordſhire,</hi> part of the Silures.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:13561:8"/>
                        <hi>Huntingdonſhire</hi> part of the ICENI.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>3. ƿestseax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naric, <hi>occidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum Saxonum regnum,</hi> the kingdome of <hi>Weſt Saxons.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Atreba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tii.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Berkeſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Hamſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Belgae.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Wiltſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Somerſetſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Durotriges.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Dorſetſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Dammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nii.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Deuonſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cornewall.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>4. Suþscaxna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ric, <hi>Auſtraliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Saxonum reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>South Saxons.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Regni.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Surrey.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>5. Centric <hi>reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Cantiorum</hi> the kingdom of <hi>Kent.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Cantii.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Kent.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>6. Eastangla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ric <hi>regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Anglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Eaſt Angles.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Icen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Norfolke.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Suffolke.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cambridgeſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The Ile of <hi>Elie.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>7. Eastscax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naric <hi>regnum orien. Saxonum</hi> the kingdom of <hi>Eaſt Saxons.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Trino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantes.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Middleſex,</hi> and part of HERTFORDSHIRE,</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe ſeauen kingdomes containe 39. ſhires, which are deuided into 22.<note place="margin">Buſhoprikes in England.</note> Biſhopricks, namely, <hi>Caunterbury, Rocheſter, Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Chicheſter, Winchester, Saliſburie, Exceter, Bath</hi> &amp; <hi>Wels, Worceſter, Gloceſter, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veforde, Couentrie</hi> &amp; <hi>Lichfield, Lincolne, Elie, Norwich, Oxford, Peterbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,</hi> &amp; <hi>Briſtow,</hi> in number 18. vnder the Archb. of Caunterburie Primate of England. <hi>Yorke, Durham, Cheſter,</hi> and <hi>Carelyle,</hi> 4. vnder the Archbiſhop of Yorke.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Cambria Wales.</head>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>CAMBRIA, WALES, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited by the Britƿea las or WAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LI BRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TANNI, is deuided into 13. ſhires.</head>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Ordoui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Flintſhire.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Denbigh.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mongomery.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Merioneth.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Caernaruan.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:13561:8"/>
                        <list>
                           <head>Silures.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Radnor.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Brecknocke.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Glamorgan.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Monmouth.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Dimaetae.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Caermarthen.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Penbroke.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Gardigan.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <head>Mona.</head>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Angleſey.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The former Heptarchie, or Countrie of 7. kingdomes,<note place="margin">The Heptarchie now a Monarchy.</note> nowe a Monarchie, moſt happely gouerned by the ſole <hi>Empres</hi> thereof moſt renowmed Queene ELIZABETH, was deuided into the former prouinces,<note place="margin">Aluredus <hi>deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſhires of England.</hi> H. 8. <hi>of Wales.</hi>
               </note> ſhieres or counties by ALVREDVS the fourth ſonne of ADOLPHVS, &amp; brother to ETHELDRED, who raigned in the yeere of Chriſt 872. But <hi>Cambria,</hi> now Wales, was diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by ſhieres, by the famous king HENRY the eight: all which ſhieres were deuided into certain parts, which the Saxons called ðrihingaf which we cal leþs or lathes,<note place="margin">Shires deuided in <hi>ðrihingaf or leþs.</hi> Ridings.</note> theſe deuiſions are yet in Kent: and Yorkeſhire at this day is diuided into Rydings, which may be alſo called ðrihingaf, all which parts conteine in them certain Hundreds, in euerie of which was conteined ten teo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>þunges, of vs called Tithings, conteining ten men,<note place="margin">Hundreds.</note> wherof it was called alſo tienmentale, a colledge or corporation of ten men,<note place="margin">Teothongs.</note> &amp; the officer of this Tithing the Saxons called teoþungmon, of vs (eſpeciallie in the Weſt) a Tythingman: in ſome places, as in Northamptonſhire, a Therdbarrow:<note place="margin">Therdbarrowes.</note> ſo that ten of theſe Tithings yeelded a 100. men, whereof the Engliſh call it at this day a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred (though the number of the men be now vncertaine) the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines call it <hi>Centuria.</hi> In ſteede of Tithings, (eſpecially beyonde Trent,) they haue Wape<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taches,<note place="margin">Centuriae. Wapentaches.</note> which the Saxons called ƿeƿon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacs, which tooke that name of the view of weapons, and where the Tenaunts deliuered vp their weapons vnto their Lords.<note place="margin">Boreſealdor.</note> The officers of theſe petite deuiſions or Tythings, are in Kent called BorHesealdors, the chiefeſt or eldeſt pledges as M.<note place="margin">M. Lamberde.</note> 
               <hi>Lamberde</hi> moſt expert in the Saxon toung affirmeth.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>Shire</hi> commeth of the Saxon Verbe Scyran,<note place="margin">Shire why ſo called.</note> which ſignifieth to cut or to deuide. Euerie of theſe Shires in time paſt was gouerned <hi>per Comitem,</hi> whom we now call Earle, who was <hi>quaſi praefectus regius,</hi> the kings Lieuetenant, who of the Saxons was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Eorle, of whom euery Shire is called a Countie, a <hi>Comite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Counties why ſo called.</note> of the Earle. But of later time there haue been, and are yeerely cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen in euery ſhire, an officer by the Prince, which in Latine is called <hi>Vicecomes,</hi> as one appointed <hi>vice Comitis</hi> in the Earles ſteed,<note place="margin">The Sherife what and whence ſo called.</note> we call him the Sherife, the Saxons called him Scyregerefa, the Reeue of the Shire, for gerefa is an officer to collect rents, and other reuenues, and to execute things vnder, &amp; for another,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13561:9"/>the Germaines at this daie haue Burgreeue of the Saxons ƿor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tgerefa,<note place="margin">Manie ſortes of Reeues.</note> the Mayor of a Towne, Margreeues, whom we cal Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbaylifes: a Landſgreue whom we call the Reeue of a Mannor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pliny, Gildas Solinus,</hi> and <hi>Martianus</hi> do agree, that this our BRITANNIA MAIOR is 800.<note place="margin">The length of Brytaine and the bredth.</note> miles in length, including alſo Scotland: and <hi>Martianus</hi> ſaith, it is in bredth 300. miles: in which dimenſuration they ſeeme to account after the Italian meaſure, which is leſſe then our myles:<note place="margin">The ſuppoſed breadth &amp; length of Englande by ſtatute meaſure.</note> yet were England meaſured accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the true and exact menſuration prouided and allowed by ſtatute, it woulde appeere to be of greater length &amp; breadth, then theſe authors account. An Italian mile containeth <hi>mille paſſus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iores,</hi> or <hi>Geometricos</hi> a 1000.<note place="margin">A myle A furlong. A pearch.</note> paces of fiue foote to the pace, which is alſo a fadome. And our Engliſh mile is eight furlongs, euery fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long 40. pearches, euery pearch 16. foote, and halfe, which maketh 5280. foote, which is more then the Italian mile by 56. paces. But our ordinary mile exceedeth both the Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; true Engliſh mile.</p>
            <p>The forme of this land is Trianguler,<note place="margin">The fertilitie of England.</note> much like Cicilia an Iſland in the middle earth ſea. The center of this land which I take to be about Titburie caſtle, hath latitude about 52. degrees, 50. minuts, and longitude 21. degrees 28. minuts. This our BRITANNIA for the fertility &amp; fruitfulnes therof, matcheth the beſt, yeelding ſuch generall commodities, &amp; in ſuch abundance, that it may be ſaid:
<q>
                  <l>Albion emporiis, tellus opulenta marinis,</l>
                  <l>fertilis omnigenum rerum:</l>
               </q>
               <hi>Another ſaith,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Anglia non ſegetes effundit diuite vena?</l>
                  <l>Paſcua non pingui fertilitate tument?</l>
                  <l>In gremio fluuiis riui miſcentur amaenis,</l>
                  <l>Gurgitibus rapidis &amp; vada pura meant.</l>
                  <l>Nobilis antiquo nutat cum robore quercus.</l>
                  <l>Et nemorum grato ſpirat odore viror.</l>
                  <l>Viſceribus mediis errant pretioſa metalla,</l>
                  <l>Diuitiae creſcunt intus, opeſque foris.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>It were too long to recite the particuler fruites, and rare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities it yeeldeth, all which are knowne to the worlde, as the Coſmographicall Poet ſaith, <hi>Omnia ſunt famatotu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vulgata per orbem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And aboue all other bleſſings it hath greateſt cauſe to reioyce in the free vſe of the true knowledge of Chriſt,<note place="margin">England most happie in the vſe of the Goſpell.</note> wherein it trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheth aboue all other kingdomes or Countries of the world, moſt happely therin maintained, (vnder the mightie king of kings, ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall lehouah) by the ſacred hand of the moſt imperial Queene ELIZABETH, the fruits of whoſe happie raigne who can enioy, &amp; not vnfeinedly commend hir ſafetie, and happie continuance, vnto that all ſufficient God, who beyond expectation, in fauour, commended hir to vs? in regarde whereof our Englande may be truely called OLBION a happie Countrie.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:13561:9"/>
            <head>SPECVLVM BRITANIAE.</head>
            <head type="sub">The first part, conteining a briefe Historicall and Chorographicall diſcription of <hi>MYDDLESEX.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing thus briefely touched the generall, I purpoſe to proceede to the particular deſcriptions of this out BRITANIA: wherein (imitating the artificial Painter, who beginneth alwaies at the head, the principall part of the bodie:) I thought it not vnfit to begin my <hi>Speculum Britaniae</hi> with MYDDLESEX,<note place="margin">The cauſes why <hi>Myddleſex</hi> is the first part of Speculum Brita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae.</note> which aboue all other Shyres is graced, with that chiefe and head Citie LONDON: which as an adamant draweth vnto it all the other parts of the land, and aboue the reſt is moſt vſuallie ferquented with hir Maieſties moſt regall preſence.</p>
            <div type="description">
               <head>Of MIDDLESEX, and of the Trinobantes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is called MIDDLESEX of the <hi>mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Saxons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Myddleſex <hi>why ſocalled.</hi>
                  </note> for that they inhabited that part betweene the <hi>East Saxons, West Saxons,</hi> and <hi>South Saxons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>MIDDLESEX was a percel of that countrey wherin (as <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaith) dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Trinobantes</hi> whom <hi>Ptolomy</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>Trinoantes,</hi> omitting the b.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Myddleſex</hi> parte of the <hi>Trinoban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</hi> Caeſar Com. Ptolomey. Galfr. Moun.</note> ſome call them <hi>Trinouantes,</hi> putting u. for b.</p>
               <p>The chiefe Citie of theſe <hi>Trino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantes,</hi> was then called <hi>Trinobantum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Colcheſter. London <hi>the Citie of the</hi> Eaſt Saxons <hi>and</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobantes. <hi>Corn.</hi> Tacitus.</note> of ſome held to be <hi>Colchester</hi> of ſome <hi>London; Beede</hi> ſaith that <hi>London</hi> was the chiefe Citie of the <hi>East Saxons,</hi> If ſo, then of neceſſitie, of the <hi>Middle ſaxons,</hi> and conſequently of the <hi>Trinobantes;</hi> yet <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaith, that <hi>London</hi> was not <hi>Trinobantum;</hi> nor the people <hi>Trinobantes,</hi> neere <hi>London,</hi> and his reaſon is that if the <hi>Trinobantes</hi> had beene neere <hi>London,</hi> they would not haue ſuffered <hi>Suetonius</hi> to haue paſſed thither; which argument <hi>Humfrey Lloyde</hi> ſeemeth to confute in this manner.<note place="margin">Humf. Lloyd.</note> The <hi>Trinobantes</hi> (ſaith he) being <hi>Suetonius</hi> enemies, would haue as well preuented him in the inner part of the countrey, as neere <hi>London,</hi> conſidering that <hi>Suetonius</hi> came from the Iſle of <hi>Angleſey,</hi> marching through the whole countrey. So that in what place ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the <hi>Trinobantes</hi> were reſident, they could not be ignorant of his paſſage.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:13561:10"/>
                  <hi>Polydore Virgile,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pollidore.</note> a man of no great credite, as touching his hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie, affirmeth from ſome other that <hi>Trinobantum</hi> was <hi>Northamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and the <hi>Northamptonſhire men Trinobantes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Northampton <hi>Tranton.</hi>
                  </note> and his reaſon is for that the countrey men in their language called that place <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> which hath no ſuch ſemblable conſonance with <hi>Trinobantum</hi> that he, or any other, ſhould ſeeke <hi>Trinobantum</hi> in that part of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Camden,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">M. Camden.</note> a ſinguler ſcrutator of antiquities ſeemeth to hold (but not abſolutely) that the <hi>Trinobantes</hi> ſhould be ſo called, of the brytiſh word <hi>Trenant,</hi> which ſignifieth townes ſcytuate in the valley.<note place="margin">Caeſar.</note> But <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaith, they inhabited <hi>Prope firmiſſimam ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum regionum ciuitatem,</hi> neere the moſt ſtrongeſt Citie in thoſe countries; which as I take was <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="description">
               <head>The lymites and principall bounds of MYDDLESEX.</head>
               <p>MYDDELSEX is ſcituate in the ſouth eaſt parte of this lande, bordering vpon the north, vpon <hi>Hertfordſhire.</hi> On the eaſt vpon <hi>Eſſex,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lea <hi>riuer.</hi>
                  </note> devided thence by the riuer <hi>Lea,</hi> and the <hi>Meere ditch:</hi> on the ſouth vpon <hi>Surrey,</hi> hauing the moſt famous riuer <hi>Thamiſe,</hi> the bound and lymite betweene them, and on the Weſt vpon <hi>Buckingham ſhire, Colne</hi> riuer and the <hi>Shire ditch,</hi> being the deuiſion betweene them.</p>
               <p>That famous riuer which is commonly of vs called <hi>Temes,</hi> is of <hi>Ptolemey</hi> called <hi>Iameſa aeſtuarium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ptolemey. Plin. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>3. Iameſa</hi> aeſtuariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> of <hi>Plinie Iameſais;</hi> of <hi>Caeſar Tameſis.</hi> It ſeemeth to be compact of two names of riuers, <hi>Tame</hi> and <hi>Iſe,</hi> which two riuers meete neere <hi>Wallingford</hi> in <hi>Barkeſhire,</hi> where after a familier manner, they louingly conioyne and vnite them ſelues, and after a kinde of Matrimoniall order, of two they become one <hi>Tame,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Thamiſe of Tame and Iſe.</note> and <hi>Iſe,</hi> becommeth <hi>Thamiſe</hi> holding that name, growing more and more famous, vntill with great pride it ſaluteth the maine ſea. The like coniunction of names is in <hi>Palestina</hi> or the <hi>holy land,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iordan of Ior and Dan.</note> where that famous riuer <hi>Iardan,</hi> is compact of <hi>Iar,</hi> which riſeth neere <hi>Mara,</hi> towardes <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> and <hi>Dan</hi> which riſeth neere, and taketh name of the Citie of <hi>Dan,</hi> both riſing out of the mountaines <hi>Lybanon,</hi> and meete at <hi>Caeſaria Philippi,</hi> where, theſe two <hi>Iar,</hi> and <hi>Dan,</hi> become <hi>Iardan,</hi> as the Poet ſaith.<note place="margin">Hunt. Coſm.</note> 
                  <hi>Iordanniſque ſacer geminis è fontibus ortus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The riuer of <hi>Thamiſe</hi> ebbeth and floweth as farre as <hi>Richmond,</hi> ſometime farther, ſome time not ſo farre, neere ſixtie miles from the maine ſea.</p>
               <p>It hath beene obſerued and affirmed by ſome that this riuer doth not eaſely increaſe with land waters. <hi>Sit experientia Iudex.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:13561:10"/>The riuer <hi>Lea,</hi> of the <hi>Saxons</hi> lig a is a proper riuer, heretofore,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lea</hi> riuer naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable in time paſt</note>(as ſome affirme) nauigable, and that ſhipping paſſed through the ſame, from the <hi>Thamiſe</hi> to <hi>Hartford.</hi> Barges haue of late paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that way, to <hi>Ware,</hi> which was granted by Acte of Parliament about the eighteene yeer of the raigne of Queene ELIZABETH, but for ſome cauſes of late diſcontinued. This riuer for the moſt part deuideth MIDDLESEX and <hi>Eastſex.</hi> But there is a ditch called the <hi>Meere ditch,</hi> about two miles and a halfe in length,<note place="margin">Meere ditch.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Waltham</hi> abbey, and Higham hill bridge which is cut into the merſhes and paſſeth through the ſame, for a diſtinction of the boundes betweene the two ſhires.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Colne</hi> riuer is the deuiſion between MIDDLESEX and <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> ſhire, But that a ditch called the <hi>Shire ditch,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Colne <hi>riuer.</hi> Shire ditch.</note> which ſeemeth to haue been forced into MIDDLESEX, about two miles in length, north of <hi>Colnebroke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Through this riuer as ſome affirme, haue paſſed ſhipping to Saint <hi>Albans. Minime credendum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="description">
               <head>The nature of the ſoyle and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitie of MYDDLESEX.</head>
               <p>MYDDLESEX is a ſmall Shire,<note place="margin">The length and circuit of <hi>Middleſex.</hi>
                  </note> in length not twentie myles, in circuite (as it were by the ring) not about 70. myles, yet for the fertilitie thereof, it may compare with any other ſhire: for the ſoyle is excellent, fat and fertile and full of profite: it yeeldeth corne and graine, not onelie in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance,<note place="margin">Middleſex <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile.</hi>
                  </note> but moſt excellent good wheate, eſpeciallie about <hi>Heston,</hi> which place may be called <hi>Granarium tritici regalis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heſton.</note> for the ſingularitie of the corne. The vaine of this eſpeciall corne ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to extend from <hi>Heston</hi> to <hi>Harrow</hi> on the hill, betweene which as in the mid way, is <hi>Periuale,</hi> more truely <hi>Pureuale.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Piriuale or pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uale.</note> In which vale is alſo <hi>Northold, Southold, Norcote, Gerneford, Hayes, &amp;c.</hi> And it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to extend to <hi>Pynner,</hi> though with ſome alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſoile. It may be noted alſo how nature hath exalted <hi>Harrow</hi> on the hill,<note place="margin">Harrow on the hill.</note> which ſeemeth to make oſtentation of it ſcituation in the <hi>Pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uale,</hi> from whence, towardes the time of Harueſt, a man may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the fields round about, ſo ſweetely to addreſſe themſelues, to the ſiocle, and ſith, with ſuch comfortable aboundaunce, of all kinde of graine, that the husbandman which waiteth for the fruits of his labours, cannot but clap his hands, for ioy, to ſee this vale, ſo to laugh and ſing.</p>
               <p>Yet doth not this ſo fruitefull ſoyle yeeld comfort, to the way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairing man in the wintertime, by reaſon of the claieſh nature of ſoyle: which after it hath raſted the Autume ſhowers, waxeth both
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13561:11"/>dyrtie and deepe: But vnto the countrie ſwaine it is as a ſweete and pleaſant garden, in regard of his hope of future profite, for
<q>
                     <l>The deepe, and dirtie loathſome ſoyle,</l>
                     <l>Yeelds golden gaine, to painefull toyle.</l>
                  </q> The induſtrious and painefull husbandman will refuſe a pallace, to droyle in theſe golden puddles.</p>
               <p>This part of MYDDDLESEX may for fertilitie compare with <hi>Tandeane,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tandeane.</note> in the weſt part of <hi>Somerſetſhire.</hi> But that <hi>Tandeane,</hi> farre ſurpaſſeth it for ſundrie fruites, and commodities, which this countrie might alſo yeelde, were it to the like imployed: but it ſeemeth they onely couet to maintaine their auncient courſe of life, and obſerue the husbandrie of their fathers, without adding, any thing to their greater profite.</p>
               <p>This ſhire is plentifullie ſtored,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Middleſex</hi> bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with faire buildinges.</note> and as it ſeemeth beautified, with manie faire, and comely buildinges, eſpecially of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of <hi>London,</hi> who haue planted their houſes of recreation not in the meaneſt places: which alſo they haue cunningly contriued, curiouſly beautified, with diuers deuiſes, neatly decked with rare invencions, inuironed with Orchards of ſundrie delicate fruites, gardens with delectable walks, arbers, allees, and great varietie of pleaſing dainties: all which ſeeme to be beautifull ornaments vnto this countrie. But who ſo turneth his eies vnto the ſtately &amp; moſt princely pallaces of Queene ELIZABETH in many parts of this ſhire moſt ſweetely ſcituate, garniſhed with moſt prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie delights, beholding alſo the houſes of Nobilitie, may ſaie as <hi>Vadian</hi> of a fruitefull and pleaſant place in <hi>Egypt, Facies istius terre pulcherima est,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vad Coſns.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The face or ſuperficies of this countrey, is moſt beautifull, the fields freſh and greene, the valleyes delightfull to behold, the townes villages and ſtately buildings enterlaced with the pleaſant woodes are glorious to be ſeene.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="description">
               <head>Of the Eccleſiaſticall and Ciuill gouernment of this Shire.</head>
               <p>FOr matter concerning Church gouernment, and order, this ſhire is vnder the iuriſdiction of the biſhop of London; which See ſometime did belong to the Archbiſhop, vntill S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time, who was called the Apoſtle of <hi>Englande,</hi> he turned the Archbiſhops See from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Caunterburie,</hi> where it continueth.</p>
               <p>And whereas all other ſhires within this land, for the moſt part, haue a perticular officer yeerely elected by hir Maieſtie, called a <hi>Sheryfe Shere-Reeue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sherife of <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſex.</hi>
                  </note> or <hi>Reeue</hi> of the ſhire: this ſhire by charter made by King IOHN, <hi>Quinto Iulii anno regni ſui</hi> 1. is in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13561:11"/>that point, vnder the high officer of the Citic of <hi>London</hi> the MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IOR: who by force of the ſame charter, yeerely conſtituteth a Sherife, within the ſame: who alſo is accountable vnto the ſaide Citie for all matters appertaining to his ſaid office.</p>
               <p>Euerie Alderman that hath beene Maior of <hi>London</hi> is Iuſtice of peace in MYDDLESEX.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Hundreds within MYDDLESEX diſtinguiſhed with theſe letters in the MAPPE.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Edmondton <hi>or</hi> Edelmeton.<note place="margin">Hundreds.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>B</hi> Goare.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>C</hi> Oſelston.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>D</hi> Istlewoorth.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>E</hi> Elthorne.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>F</hi> Spelthorne.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Market Townes in MYDDLESEX.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Westminster.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Market towes.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Brentforde.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Stanes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vxbridge,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Harrow</hi> on the hill, was a market towne in the time of Doct. <hi>Bordes</hi> perigrination as appeereth by a little Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of his in writing.</item>
               </list>
               <p>It is to be noted that this ſhire hath in it manie Chappels of eaſe, that haue the name of pariſh Churches: as <hi>Vxbridge</hi> a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket towne belongeth to great <hi>Hellingdon: Brentford</hi> a market town belongeth to great <hi>Eling,</hi> manie mo there are within this ſhire which to expreſſe would be too tedious.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Houſes of Lawe. THere are two houſes of <hi>Iudges</hi> and <hi>Searieants,</hi> called <hi>Seriantes Innes,</hi> the one in Fleeſtreere the other in Chauncerie Lane.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Innes</hi> of Courte are fower.
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Inner Temple.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Middle Temple.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Lyncolnes Inne.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Greyes Inne.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:13561:12"/>
                     <hi>Innes</hi> of the Chauncery 8.
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Clyffords Inne.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Dauydes</hi> or <hi>Thauyes Inne.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Furniuals Inne.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Barnards Inne.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Staple Inne.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Clements Inne.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Newe Inne.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Lyons Inne.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Battles in MYDLESEX noted thus <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
                  </head>
                  <item>NEere <hi>Barnet</hi> in <hi>Enfielde Chace,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Polid vir. Tho. Walſ.</note> was a battle fought between EDWARD the fourth, and the fauourites of HENRIE the ſixt.</item>
                  <item>Neere <hi>Brentforde</hi> was a conflict betweene <hi>Edmond Iron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide</hi> and the Danes.<note place="margin">Tho. Walſ.</note>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Parkes of hir Maieſties within MYDDLESEX. THis Shire is plentifully furniſhed with hir MAIESTIES <hi>Parkes,</hi> for prinecly delights, exceeding all the kingdome of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> wherein are not ſo manie, (if the diſcourſe be true which is made of a debate betweene an Heraulde of <hi>England,</hi> and a Herauld of <hi>Fraunce</hi>) where it is affirmed that there are in all that Region but two <hi>Parkes:</hi> In MYDDLESEX are ten of hir MAIESTIES.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>S. Iames Parke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hyde Parke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Marybone Parke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hanwoorth Parke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Kenton Parke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hampton Courte Parkes,</hi> two.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Enfielde Parkes,</hi> two.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Twickenham Parke,</hi> diſperked.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Hilles of name.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Harrow hill.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hamsted hill.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Highgate hill.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of Middlesex</figDesc>
                  <head>MYDDLESEX</head>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <head>Caracters diſtinguiſhing the difference of places</head>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap> Market townes</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap> Pariſhes</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap> Hamletes or villages</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap> Howſes &amp; Palaces of Quen Eli</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap> Howſes of Nobilitie</item>
                        <item>
                           <g ref="char:circdot">⊙</g> Howſes of Knightes, Gent. &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap> Caſtles &amp; fortes</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap> Monaſteries or religious howſes</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap> Buſhops Seas</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap> Hoſpitales</item>
                        <item>
                           <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Places where battells have bene</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap> Decayde places</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap> Lodges in foreſtes chaſes &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap> Mylles.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <byline>Ioannes Norden Angl. deſcripſit 1593</byline>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:13561:13"/>
            </div>
            <div type="description">
               <pb facs="tcp:13561:14"/>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:13561:14"/>
               <head>Olde and auncient highwaies now vnaccuſtomed.</head>
               <p>THe old and auncient high waie to high <hi>Bernet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Port Poole.</note> from <hi>Porte-Poole,</hi> now <hi>Grayes Inne,</hi> as alſo from <hi>Clerkenwell,</hi> was through a lane, on the eaſt of <hi>Pancras Church,</hi> called <hi>Longwich lane.</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence, leauing <hi>Highgate</hi> on the weſt, it paſſed through <hi>Tallingdone lane</hi> and ſo to <hi>Crouch ende,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tallingdon lane.</note> and thence through a Parke called <hi>Harnſey great parke,</hi> to <hi>Muſwell hill,</hi> to <hi>Coanie hatch, Fryarne Barnet,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Whetstone,</hi> which is now the common high way to high <hi>Bernet.</hi> This auncient high way, was refuſed of wayfaring men, and carriers, by reaſon of the deepenes and dirtie paſſage in the winter ſeaſon: In regard whereof it was agreed betweene the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and the Countrie, that a newe waie ſhoulde bee layde forth through the ſaid Biſhops parks, beginning at <hi>Highgate hill,</hi> to leade (as nowe is accuſtomed) directly to <hi>Whestone:</hi> for which newe waie all cartes, carriers, packmen, and ſuch like tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellers, yeelde a certaine tole vnto the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Highgate tole.</note> which is fermed (as is ſaid at this daie) at 40. <hi>li. per annum.</hi> and for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, was the gate erected on the hill, that through the ſame all traueilers ſhoulde paſſe, and be the more aptlie ſtaide for the ſame tole.</p>
               <p>Another auncient high waie which did leade to <hi>Edgworth,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Saint Albons,</hi> was ouer <hi>Hampsted</hi> heath, and thence to, and through an old lane, called <hi>Hendon wante,</hi> neere <hi>Hendon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hendon want.</note> through which it paſſed to <hi>Edgwoorth,</hi> whence it paſſed ouer <hi>Brokeley hilles,</hi> through part of <hi>Hertfordſhire,</hi> by <hi>Radnet, Colnestreete, Saint Stephens,</hi> and <hi>Saint Mychaels,</hi> leauing <hi>Saint Albons,</hi> halfe a mile in the eaſt. This way of ſome is helde to be <hi>Watlingstreete,</hi> one of the fower high waies, which <hi>Bellinus</hi> cauſed to be made, &amp; leadeth (as ſome affirme) through <hi>Watlingstreete</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="index_of_place_names">
               <head>An Alphabet of the Cities, Townes, Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, Villages, and howſes of name within MID<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DELSEX, conteined in the Map of the Shire, with ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie annotations vpon ſundrie of them. The vſe of which Alphabet is ſet down, before to the Reader.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>A.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aſcot.</hi> E. 8.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Augustines</hi> lodge. H. 18. a lodge in Enfield chace.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:13561:15"/>
                     <hi>Acton</hi> eaſt F. 14.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Acton</hi> weſt G. 14.<note place="margin">Baron of Burford buried.</note> The <hi>Barron</hi> of <hi>Burford</hi> died there, as he paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from <hi>London,</hi> and is couered with a Marble ſtone, in the yeere of Chriſt 1527.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aſhford</hi> I. 8. So called of the brooke or ford through which men paſſe at that place.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Astleham</hi> I. 8.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>B.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Breakeſpeare.</hi> E. 4. The houſe of <hi>George Aſhby</hi> Eſquire.</item>
                  <item>* <hi>Brockenborrowes</hi> E. 6. There dwelleth <hi>Gomerſale</hi> Gentleman.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Brownſwell</hi> E. 4. a Well in the high way from <hi>Highgate</hi> to <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net,</hi> the water whereof is a ſweete refreſhment often times to we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and thirſtie poore trauellers, of late reedified by ſome well diſpoſed.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Burye</hi> ſtreete B. 20. a Hamlet of Enfield.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Buls</hi> lodge A. 18. a lodge of Enfield chace.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Belſiſe</hi> E. 16. the houſe of <hi>William Wade</hi> Eſquire, one of the clerkes of hir Maieſties preuy Counſell.</item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Brentſtreete</hi> E. 14. So called of the riuer or brooke called <hi>Brent</hi> through which it runneth.<note place="margin">Brent riuer.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is to be noted that at this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>ſtreete</hi> many yeers ſince dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Brents,</hi> among who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Iohn Brent</hi> who died <hi>Anno Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti</hi> 1467. whoſe aunceſtors before him had there, their reſidence,</p>
                     <p>This <hi>Iohn</hi> lieth buried at <hi>Hendon</hi> vnder a marble ſtone, with his picture and the time of his diſceaſe: whereby it ſeemeth that the ſtreete tooke name of the <hi>Brentes,</hi> and the brooke of the ſtreete, and heereof alſo doth,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Brentforde</hi> H. 12. commonly called new <hi>Brentford</hi> or <hi>Brayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde,</hi> or <hi>Market Brentforde</hi> take name, for that <hi>Brent</hi> brooke paſſeth through the towne. This <hi>Brentford</hi> is a market towne, yet no pariſh, but belongeth vnto great <hi>Elinge.</hi> It is called new <hi>Brent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> as I take it of the late purchaſe of the market which was in the time of king <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt:<note place="margin">Brentford why ſo called.</note> for the chappel argueth it of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter antiquity then the other, which hath the name of old <hi>Brentford.</hi> of the river <hi>Brent,</hi> which runneth on the weſt part of the towne, and betweene it and <hi>Syon</hi> entreth into the <hi>Thames.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This worde <hi>Brent</hi> among the countrey people, of thoſe partes, ſignifieth,<note place="margin">Brent, the word how the people take the ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> and is taken for all brookes, riuers, and currants of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, therefore is euerie ſmall brooke called the <hi>Brent</hi> among them.</p>
                     <p>Neere vnto this place <hi>Edmond Ironſide,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Edm. Ironſides</hi> conflict with the Danes.</note> aſſaulted the <hi>Danes</hi> which he had driuen from the ſiedge of <hi>London,</hi> and there put manie of them to the ſword, and put the reſidue to flight, about <hi>anno Chriſti</hi> 1016. the place appeereth by this carracter <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:13561:15"/>
                     <hi>Brentford old</hi> H. 14. a little thorowfare.</item>
                  <item>*<hi>Buſhoppes hall</hi> F. 22. the houſe of the Lord <hi>Wentwoorth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Blackwall,</hi> G. 22. neere which is a harbor in the <hi>Thamis</hi> for ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping,<note place="margin">Blackwall why ſo called.</note> the place taketh name of the blackenes or darkenes of the water bankes, or wall at that place.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Brompton</hi> G. 16.</item>
                  <item>** <hi>Boston</hi> G. 12. where dwelleth <hi>Iherome Halley</hi> Eſquire.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bedfont west</hi> H. 6.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bedfont east</hi> H. 8.</item>
                  <item>* <hi>Brumfielde</hi> C. 20. the houſe of <hi>Skeuington</hi> Eſquire.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>C.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cannons</hi> D. 10.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Crowch ende</hi> D. 18.</item>
                  <item>* <hi>Coanie Hatch</hi> D. 18. there dwelleth <hi>Trot</hi> Gentleman.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Clapton</hi> E. 22.</item>
                  <item>** <hi>Canburie</hi> or <hi>Cannonburie</hi> E. 20. a houſe in the hands of <hi>Atee</hi> Gentleman. It was builded by prior <hi>Bolton</hi> prior of Saint <hi>Bartholmewes</hi> in <hi>Smithfield</hi> in the time of H. 8.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Childes hill</hi> E. 16.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Chalcot</hi> or <hi>Chalkhill</hi> E. 16.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cowley</hi> F. 6.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Chelſey</hi> G. 18.<note place="margin">Chelſey why ſo called.</note> So called of the nature of the place whoſe ſtrond is like the cheſel which the ſea caſteth vp of ſand &amp; pebble ſtones. Therof called <hi>Cheſelſey</hi> breefely <hi>Chelſey,</hi> as is <hi>Chelſey</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> north of <hi>Chychester,</hi> which ſtandeth vpon the very edge of the ſea, as this * <hi>Chelſey</hi> on the <hi>Thamiſe.</hi> Queene ELIZABETH hath there a faire houſe: The Lord <hi>Dacres</hi> hath there a faire houſe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cheſwicke</hi> H. 14. belonging to a prebend of Paules now in the handes of Doctor <hi>Goodman</hi> Deane of <hi>Westminster,</hi> where he hath a faire houſe, whereunto (in the time of any common plague or ſicknes) as alſo to take the aire, he withdraweth the ſchollers of the colledge of <hi>Westminster.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>* <hi>Colham, Collumbe,</hi> or <hi>Colneham,</hi> G. 6. a houſe of the Earle of <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies,</hi> which taketh name <hi>Colneham</hi> of the ſcytuation thereof ſo neere a branch of <hi>Colne</hi> ſtreame.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Colbrooke</hi> or <hi>Colnebroke</hi> G. 6. one little part wherof is in MID<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DLESEX as farre as the bridge, the reſt is <hi>Buckingham ſhire.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Craneford</hi> H. 8. It is ſo called of the forde or brooke called by the name of <hi>Crane.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Carleton</hi> or <hi>Charleton</hi> K. 8.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>D.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dalis</hi> D. 14.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dryuers hill</hi> D. 14.</item>
                  <item>* <hi>Durance</hi> B. 20. the houſe of <hi>Robert Wroth</hi> Eſquire.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:13561:16"/>** <hi>Durhams</hi> B. 14.<note place="margin">Lacye Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman.</note> a houſe in the hands of</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Daleſon hill</hi> E. 14.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dormans well</hi> F. 10. the houſe of the <hi>Lo. Dacres.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>* <hi>Drayton</hi> G. 6. a houſe late the Lord <hi>Pagets.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>E.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edgeworth</hi> D. 12. conſiſting of one maine ſtreete, the weſt ſide whereof belongeth to little <hi>Stanmer</hi> called alſo <hi>Whitchurch</hi> the other part hath a church in it ſelfe.<note place="margin">ƿorþ</note> ƿorþ in the <hi>Saxon</hi> toong ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth a place fruitefull, and fit in regarde of the apt ſcytuation thereof to be inhabited this ƿorþ ſtanding on the very edge of the ſhire may be called <hi>Edgeworth,</hi> of ſome but corruptly <hi>Edge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>East end</hi> D. 16. a member of <hi>Finchley.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Edmondton</hi> or <hi>Edelmeton</hi> C. 20. In the Church whereof, are ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ancient monuments, the moſt of them defaced, among which is a tombe of gray Marble circumſcribed thus.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hic iacent corpora Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae Carleton cuiuſda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dni.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Thomas Careleton buried.</note> 
                        <hi>iſtius villae qui obiit</hi> 21. <hi>die Februar: Anno Do.</hi> 1447. <hi>&amp; Elizabethae vxo ris eius. filiae Adae Francis militis per quam habuit dominium,</hi> whoſe arms are theſe.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>There is alſo one <hi>Iohn Kirketon</hi> Eſquire,<note place="margin">Iohn Kirketen buried.</note> whoſe monument is of white free ſtone erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſouth wall of the Church, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth as auncient as the Church it ſelfe, but there is no record of the time of his deceaſe, his armes are theſe.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>There is a fable of one <hi>Peter Fabell</hi> that lyeth in the ſame Church alſo,<note place="margin">Peter Fabell bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried.</note> who is ſaide to haue beguiled the Deuell by pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie for money, But the Deuell is deceite it ſelfe, and hardly deceiued.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edmonton</hi> ſtreete C. 20.</item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Enfield</hi> B. 20. ſometime parcell of the land of the Duke of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caster</hi> now Queene <hi>Elizabeths.</hi> The chace called <hi>Enfield chace</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth name of this place.</p>
                     <p>It is called of ſome <hi>Enfen</hi> and ſo recorded,<note place="margin">Enfen.</note> in regarde of the Fenny ſcytuation of ſome part thereof vpon the marſhes or mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ground, which (though now brought to be good meadow and profitable paſture) it hath beene in time paſt fenney: thereof taking the name <hi>Enfen</hi> or <hi>Infen,</hi> now <hi>Enfielde.</hi> But theſe fenney grounds are now on the eaſt, as the chace in the weſt, profitable neighbors not onely vnto <hi>Enfield,</hi> but to many other poore inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants neere.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Elinge</hi> called great <hi>Elinge</hi> G. 12.<note place="margin">Thomas frowike buried.</note> In the Church whereof lyeth buried <hi>Thomas Frowike</hi> ſometime owner of <hi>Gunnersbury</hi> or <hi>Gunwelſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> an auncient ſeat within the ſame pariſh.
<figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eueney</hi> H. 6. a ferme houſe belonging vnto the Deane and chapter of <hi>Westminſter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Enfielde</hi> houſe A. 20. Queene ELIZABETHS, builded by an Earle of <hi>Worcester.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:13561:17"/>
                  <head>F.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Frith</hi> called alſo <hi>New hall</hi> D. 14. ſometime the <hi>Therlebyes</hi> now <hi>Richard Weekes</hi> Gentleman,<note place="margin">Lord Frowike.</note> by purchace.</item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Finchley</hi> D. 16. In the Church whereof ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Lord <hi>Frowyke,</hi> Lord chiefe Iuſtice of England, in the time of H. 6. vnder a Marble toombe where hath beene his picture and armes in braſſe, with circumſcription about the toombe, but now defaced, his armes one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remayning in the chauncell window in this manner.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>There is alſo another Marble ſtone hauing the picture of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man whereon is inſcribed thus.</p>
                     <q>Ioan la feme Thomas de Frowicke gist icy, &amp; le dit Thomas Penſe de giſer aueque luy.</q>
                     <p>There lyeth alſo buried vnder a Marble ſtone in the Chauncell of the Church one <hi>Thomas Aldenham</hi> Eſquire ſometime Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to King <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſixt who died in <hi>Anno</hi> 1431.<note place="margin">Thomas Aldeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</note> his armes.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fryarne Barnet</hi> C. 18.</item>
                  <item>** <hi>Fryarne Mannor</hi> C. 18. Sir <hi>Iohn Popham</hi> knight Lord chiefe Iuſtice of England, ſometime maketh there his abode.</item>
                  <item>** The <hi>Folde</hi> B. 16. the houſe of</item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fulham</hi> H. 16. of the <hi>Saxons</hi> called fullonham (which as Maſter <hi>Camden</hi> taketh it) ſignifieth <hi>Volucrum domus,</hi> the habitacle of birdes or the place of fowles, fullon and fuglas in the <hi>Saxon</hi> toong doe ſignifie fowles, and Ham or Hame as much as home in our toong. So that fullon Ham or fuglasHame is as much to ſaie, as the home houſe or habitacle of fowle. It may be alſo taken for <hi>Volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum amnis</hi> the riuer of fowle, for Ham alſo in many places ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth <hi>Amnis</hi> a riuer. But it is moſt probable it ſhould be of lande fowle which vſually haunt groues, and cluſters of trees, whereof in this place it ſee-meth hath beene plentie.</p>
                     <p>* There is an auncient houſe belonging to the ſea of <hi>London</hi> moated aboute. <hi>Henry</hi> the third often lay at this place.</p>
                     <p>The hoſte of the pagan <hi>Danes</hi> in the time of K. <hi>Alphred</hi> did win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13561:17"/>there, in the yeere of Chriſt 879. the woodes,<note place="margin">Galfr. mon. Greg. inpast.</note> and apt ſcytua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the place, for paſſage by water (no doubt) moued them thereunto.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Feltham</hi> I. 8.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Feltham hill</hi> I. 8.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>G.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gernford</hi> F. 10. a very fertile place of corne ſtanding in the <hi>pure vale.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gunnersbury</hi> or <hi>Gunwelsbury</hi> G. 14. an auncient houſe well ſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate for wood, water, and ayre ſometime the <hi>Frowickes</hi> now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the ** Corbets,</item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Gyles</hi> in the fielde F. 18. erected by <hi>Matylde</hi> Queene to H. 1.<note place="margin">Rex. E. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> for leprous people about <hi>Anno</hi> 1117.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>H.</head>
                  <item>* <hi>Harefield</hi> E. 4. There Sir <hi>Edmond Anderſon</hi> knight, Lord chiefe Iuſtice of the common plecs, hath a faire houſe ſtanding on the edge of the hill. The riuer <hi>Colne</hi> paſſing neere the ſame through the pleaſant meddowes and ſweete paſtures yeelding both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and profit.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Highwood hill</hi> D. 12. a member of little <hi>Stanmer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hendon</hi> D. 14. of the <hi>Saxous</hi> Highendune,<note place="margin">Hendon why ſo called.</note> which ſignifieth <hi>Highwood</hi> of the plentie of wood there growing on the hils.</item>
                  <item>* <hi>Hendon houſe</hi> D. 14. the mannor houſe of <hi>Hendon,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Herbertes</hi> knight: where nowe is often reſident <hi>Iohn Forteſcue</hi> Eſquire, one of hir Maieſties moſt honorable priuie Counſell, when he taketh the ayre in the Countrey.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hollicke,</hi> D. 18. there are noted the foundations of ancient buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, affirmed by ſome aged men that it hath beene a Towne. but oftentimes, <hi>Immenſa cani ſpirant mendatia folles.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Harnſey,</hi> of ſome <hi>Horneſey,</hi> D. 20. a pariſh ſtanding neere the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Londons woodes or parkes, which of that place heereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had and yet retaine the names of <hi>Harnſey</hi> parkes.</p>
                     <p>The Church of <hi>Harnſey</hi> is ſuppoſed to be built with the ſtones that came from the ruines of <hi>Lodghill.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hadley,</hi> B. 16.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Holway the lower,</hi> E. 20.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Holway the vpper,</hi> E. 18.</item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Highgate,</hi> E. 18. a hill ouer which is a paſſage,<note place="margin">Highgate why ſo called.</note> and at the top of the ſame hill is a gare through which all maner paſſengers haue their waie; the place taketh the name of the highgate on the hill, which gate was erected at the alteration of the way, which (as is ſaide before) was on the eaſt of <hi>Highgate.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When the way was turned ouer the ſaide hill to leade through
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13561:18"/>the parke of the Biſhop of London as nowe it doth, there was in regard thereof,<note place="margin">A tole at High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate.</note> a tole raiſed vpon ſuch as poſſed that way with carriage. And for that no paſſenger ſhoulde eſcape, without paieng tole by reaſon of the widenes of the waie, this gate was raiſed, through which of neceſſitie all traueilers paſſe. This tole is nowe fermed of the ſaid Biſhop at fortie pound <hi>per annum.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At this place is a free ſchole builded of bricke by ſir ROGER CHOLMELEY knight,<note place="margin">A free ſchoole.</note> ſometime Lorde chiefe Iuſtice of <hi>England</hi> about the yeere of Chriſt 1564. The pencion of the maſter is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine: there is no vſher, and the ſchole is in the diſpoſition of ſixe governors or feffees.</p>
                     <p>Where now the ſchole ſtandeth,<note place="margin">An heremitage at Highgate. A Cawſway be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Highgate and Iſlington.</note> was an Hermytage, and the Hermyte cauſed to be made the cauſway betweene <hi>Highgate</hi> and <hi>Iſlyngton,</hi> and the grauell was had from the top of <hi>Highgate</hi> hill, where now is a ſtanding ponde of water.</p>
                     <p>There is adioining vnto the ſchole a chapple for the eaſe of that part of the countrey, for that they are within the pariſh of <hi>Pancras</hi> which is diſtant thence neere two miles.</p>
                     <p>Vpon this hill is moſt pleaſant dwelling, yet not ſo pleaſant as healthfull, for the expert inhabitants there, report that diuers that haue beene long viſited with ſicknes, not cureable by Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, haue in ſhort time, repayred their health by that ſweete ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutarie aire.</p>
                     <p>** At this place CORNEWALLEYES eſquire,<note place="margin">Cornwallis eſquire</note> hath a verie faire houſe from which he may with great delight beholde the ſtately Citie of <hi>London, Westminster, Greenewich,</hi> the famous river of <hi>Thamyſe,</hi> and the countrey towardes the ſouth verie farre.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hamsted,</hi> E. 16. ſtandeth vnder a hill, in a verie healthfull ayre, hauing <hi>London</hi> in verie pleaſant perſpect. In the church thereof lieth M. ARMIGELL WAADE eſquire, in a faire monument of Alablaſter raiſed in the wall of the Chauncell with this inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="inscription">
                                 <head>Memoriae ſacrum.</head>
                                 <p>Optimis &amp; chariſſimis parentibus <hi>ARMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GELLO WAADO</hi> è Brigantium antiqua fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia oriundo,<note place="margin">Armigell Waad Eſquire buried.</note> 
                                    <hi>HEN. 8.</hi> &amp; <hi>EDW. 6.</hi> Regum Secretori concilio ab epiſtolis, &amp; in agro <hi>Middleſexiano</hi> Eirenarchae qui in maximarum artium diſciplinis, prudentiaque ciuili instructiſſimus, plurimarum linguarum callentiſſimus, legationibus honoratiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis perfunctus, &amp; inter Britannos Indiarum A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mericarum explorator primus. Ex duabus coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus,
<figure>
                                       <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                                    </figure> 
                                    <hi>ALICIA PATENIA,</hi> &amp; <hi>ANNA MERBVRIA, 20.</hi> liberos progenuis, tandemque post vitam, honorifice &amp; pientiſſimè defunctam an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13561:18"/>virginei partus <hi>1568.</hi> Menſis Iunii die <hi>20.</hi> in domino placide obdormuit. Et <hi>ALICIAE PATENIAE</hi> quae patri <hi>17.</hi> libros peperit, è quibus duo mares &amp; tres femellae, adhuc in viuis existunt quae vita caſtiſſime &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratiſſimè tranſacta, anno ſalutis humanae <hi>1568.</hi> animam pientiſſimam Redemptori reddidit.</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>GVLIELMVS WAADVS</hi> filius maeximus natu, &amp; heres, Idemque diuae <hi>ELIZABETHE</hi> Reginae concilio Secretori ab epistolis, hoc monument um poſuit.</p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Harrow</hi> on the hill, E. 10. ſtanding verie high, in a place both pleaſaunt and ftuitefull, and though loftely mounted on a hill, yet in reaſonable ſort watered.</p>
                     <p>In the ile of the church lieth buried M. WILLIAM GERARD Eſquire &amp; DORATHEY his wife,<note place="margin">William Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard eſquire bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried.</note> who dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at <hi>Flamberds,</hi> ſo called of the <hi>Flamberdes,</hi> who ſomtime poſſeſſed the ſame, this WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM GERARD deceaſed the 15. <hi>Apr.</hi> 1583.<note place="margin">Flamberds.</note> and they both lie in a tombe of white marble, raiſed in the wall.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>Diuers of the <hi>Flamberds</hi> of <hi>Flamberdes</hi> a hamlet in <hi>Harrow,</hi> are interred in the ſame Church, among whom is one IOHN FLAM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ERDS, on whoſe tombe is thus inſcribed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ion me do marmore numinis ordine flam tumulatur.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Barde quoque verbere ſtigis è funere hic tueatur.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iohn Lyons</hi> his gift to the erection of a free ſchoole.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>There is a ſchoole in <hi>Harow,</hi> as yet not a free ſchoole, but inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be, and one IOHN LYONS Gent hath giuen (after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe to be imployed towards the erection and founding therof,) 300. pound, and 30. pound <hi>per ann.</hi> for a Maſter, and 10. pound for an Vſher (as it is informed) a preſident good to be followed of the able.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hellingdon</hi> great F. 6.<note place="margin">Lorde <hi>Strange</hi> burted.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the church lieth buried vnder a tombe couered with a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell ſtone, the Lord STRANGE whoſe tombe is circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcribed thus, <q>
                           <hi>Sub hac tumba iacet nobilis</hi> IOHANNES <hi>dominue le</hi> STRANGE, <hi>Dominus</hi> de Knocking, Mahun, Waſſet, Warnell, <hi>&amp;</hi> Lacy, <hi>&amp; Dominus de</hi> Colham, <hi>vna cum pictura</hi> IAGNETTAE <hi>quondam vxoris ſuae: quae quidem</hi> IAGNETTA, <hi>fuit ſoror</hi> ELIZABETHAE <hi>Reginae</hi> Angliae <hi>quondam vxoris Regis</hi> EDW. 4. <hi>qui quidem</hi> IOHAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NES <hi>obiit.</hi> 15. <hi>die Octobris Anno regni Regis</hi> EDW. 4.17. <hi>quam qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem tumbam</hi> IOHANNA <hi>Domina le</hi> STRANGE <hi>filia &amp; heres predicti</hi> IOHANNIS <hi>&amp;</hi> IAGNETTAE, <hi>vnacu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pictura</hi> IOHAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAE <hi>ex ſumptibus ſuis propriis, fieri fecit</hi> 1509.</q>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>* <hi>Hayes,</hi> F. 8. belongeth to the Lord <hi>Dacres,</hi> and Lord <hi>North.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Harleſtone</hi> greene, F. 14.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hockeſdone,</hi> F. 20. belonging to a Prebend of Paules.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13561:19"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hackeney</hi> or <hi>Hacquenye,</hi> F. 22. In the church thereof lieth buried,<note place="margin">Chriſtopher Vrſwyke <hi>buried.</hi>
                        </note> one CHRISTOPHER VRSWYKE whoſe chiefe monument is erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of white free ſtone, in the north ſide of the Chauncell, yet was he interred in the middle of the ſame Chauncell, couered with a faire graie Marble ſtone; pictured in braſſe with this ſubſcription.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <q>CHRISTOPHERVS VRSVVICVS <hi>Regis</hi> HENRICI <hi>ſeptimi Elimoſinarius; vir ſua aetate clarus, ſummantibus at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> intimatibus cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, Ad exteros reges vndecies pro patria legatus, Deconatum</hi> Eborum <hi>Archidiaconatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        </hi> Richmondiae, <hi>Deconatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        </hi> Windeſoriae <hi>habitos, viuens reliquit, Epiſcopatum Norwicenſem oblatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recuſauit: Magnos honores, tota vita ſpreuit: ſnugali vita contentus, hic viuere, hic mori maluit: plenus annis obijt, ab omnibus deſideratus, funeris pompam, etiam teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento vetuit: hic ſepultus, carnis reſurectionem, in aduentum Christi expectat: obijt Anno Dommini</hi> 1521, 24, <hi>die Octobr.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>The men of our time, who more greedelie thirſt for high and great preferments, then for the diligent execution of their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and feeding of Gods people; may by this godly mans exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be mooued, ſomthing to mortefie their greedy affections, and onioying onely a ſufficient portion, to endeuour rather the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Church of God then their owne glory, And in time to caſt away thoſe things that hinder their going one, in a ſincere courſe of life.</p>
                     <p>In the ſame chauncell is the coat armour, ſhild garter and creſt of the Earle of Northumberland.<note place="margin">Earle of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the Church in the north Ile thereof is rayſed a moſt faire and famous monument of Marble and Alablaſter, very curiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie contriued, whereon lyeth very neatly figured, the picture and corporall proportion, of the Lady <hi>Lucy,</hi> daughter to the Earle of <hi>Worcester,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The Lady Laty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer buried.</note> wife vnto fir <hi>Iohn Neuell</hi> knight Lord <hi>Latymer,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed at his mannour of <hi>Snape</hi> in <hi>Yorkeſhire.</hi> The ſaid Lady de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed <hi>Anno</hi> 1582. hauing iſſue, foure daughters, <hi>Katherine</hi> the eldeſt maried <hi>Henry</hi> Earle of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> who by her had iſſue <hi>Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Percie, Thomas, William Charles, Richard, Allyn, Ioſſalyne and George,</hi> Lady <hi>Iane, Lucy,</hi> and <hi>Elinor.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Dorathy</hi> the ſecond daughter maried ſir <hi>Thomas Cecill</hi> knight, who by hir had iſſue <hi>William, Richard, Edward, Christopher,</hi> and <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Katherine, Lucy, Myldred, Mary, Suſan, Elizabeth, Dorathy,</hi> and <hi>Frances.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lucy</hi> the third daughter maried <hi>William Cornwallys</hi> Eſquire by whom ſhe had iſſue, <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Iohn, Ione, Frances, Elizabeth,</hi> and <hi>Katherine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="25" facs="tcp:13561:19"/>
                        <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the firſt and youngeſt daughter maried ſir <hi>Iohn Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers</hi> knight, by whom ſhe had iſſue <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>Henry, Anne, Lucy, Elienor,</hi> and <hi>Mary.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>One <hi>Heron</hi> Eſqire founded <hi>Hacquenie</hi> Church, and lyeth buried in the north Ile,<note place="margin">Heron Eſquire buried.</note> in a toombe of white free ſtone his armes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare ingrauen in ſtone in euery piller of the ſame Church thus,</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>In the ſame Church in the ſouth Ile was buried <hi>Roe</hi> knight,<note place="margin">Roe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman buried.</note> ſometime Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> his monument is of marble and Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaſter.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hamerſmith,</hi> G. 16.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hamerſmith hoſpitall,</hi> G. 16.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Harlington,</hi> G. 8.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Harmeſwoorth,</hi> or <hi>Harmundeſwoorth,</hi> G. 6.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Heston,</hi> H. 10. a moſt fertyle place of wheate
<figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure> yet not ſo much to be commended for the quantitie, as for the qualitie, for the wheat is moſt pure, accompted the pureſt in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſhires. And therefore Queene ELIZABETH hath the moſt part of her proviſion from that place for manchet for her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes owne diet, as is reported.</item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hounſlow</hi> or <hi>Hunſlow,</hi> H. 10. belongeth vnto two pariſhes, the north ſide of the ſtreete to <hi>Heston,</hi> and the ſouth to <hi>Istlewoorth:</hi> But there is a chappell of eaſe, which belonged vnto the fryerie there diſſolued, which friery after the diſſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was by exchange giuen to the Lord <hi>Windſore,</hi> by King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight. Afterwardes it came to Auditor <hi>Roan</hi> by purchace who hath beſtowed the ſame chappell, and 40. ſhillings <hi>per annum</hi> vpon the inhabitantes to the ende and vpon condition that they by farther contribution ſhall maintaine a miniſter there.</p>
                     <p>* There is a faire houſe erected where the friery was: belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the heires of Auditor <hi>Roan.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the chappell was buried ſir <hi>George Windſore</hi> knight in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of white free ſtone, rayſed with foure pillers.<note place="margin">Sir George Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore buried.</note> In that place lie many other of the <hi>Windſores.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hanworth</hi> I. 10. a houſe of hir Maieſties.</item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hampton Court</hi> K. 12. an honour of Queene ELIZABETHES, a moſt regall pallace ſtately rayſed of bricke after a moſt princely forme, by Cardinall WOVLSEY moſt pleaſantly, ſcytuate vpon delightſome <hi>Thamiſe.</hi> Queene ELIZABETH hath of late cauſed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13561:20"/>a very bewtifull fountaine,<note place="margin">A fountaine erected at Hampton-court.</note> there to be erected, in the ſecond court which graceth the pallace, and ſerueth to great and neceſſarie vſe, the fountaine was finiſhed in <hi>Anno</hi> 1590. not without great charge.</p>
                     <p>It is called <hi>Hampton Court</hi> of the pariſh of <hi>Hampton,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hampton Court why ſo called.</note> which ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not far thence: and <hi>Court</hi> commeth of <hi>Curia,</hi> which was the place where the <hi>Senate</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> aſſembled, and was taken for the <hi>Senate</hi> it ſelfe, And thereof groweth our word <hi>Court,</hi> which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all aſſemblies either for tryall of controuerſies, or conſulting of matters of ſtate, as alſo it is amongſt vs vſed as an adiunct, to diuers houſes in this land of greateſt antiquitie, as the moſt aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient houſe in a mannor called the <hi>Court houſe.</hi> But this word <hi>Court</hi> is hereunto added neither in regard of antiquitie, nor head houſe of a mannor. But in regard of the Maieſtie and Princely bewtie thereof, fit for none but for a King or Queene, whoſe reſidence in any place draweth a Princely aſſembly, which is called the <hi>Court,</hi> for where hir Maieſty is reſident there is the Court of ſtate. This word Court is a moſt common adiunct to places of antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in <hi>Artetia,</hi> as alſo in diuers prouinces of <hi>France</hi> and elſe where as <hi>Haplincourt,</hi> in <hi>Normandy, Bonlayn Court</hi> in <hi>Champaigne,</hi> and <hi>Hall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court</hi> neere <hi>Amyens.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There are belonging to this princely pallace two parkes,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Parkes at</hi> Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Court.</note> the one of Deare, the other of hares, both inuironed with wals of bricke, the ſouth ſide of the Deare parke, excepted, which is paled and inuironed with the <hi>Thamiſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hampton</hi> K. 12.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hanuerde</hi> or <hi>Hanforde</hi> K. 8.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ickenham</hi> E. 6.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſlington</hi> or <hi>Iſeldon</hi> E. 20. belonging to a prebend of <hi>Paules.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>S. Ieames</hi> G. 18. hir Maieſties, a very ſtately houſe, built after a quadranguler forme, by the famous King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>K.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Kyckeſende</hi> B. 16.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Kingſland</hi> E. 20.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Kentiſhtowne</hi> E. 18.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Kylbourne</hi> or <hi>Keelebourne,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Kylbourne</hi> why ſo called.</note> E. 16. ſeemeth to take name of Keele, and bourn which ſignifie colde water: It is called in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords <hi>Kullebourne.</hi> In the time of <hi>H.</hi> the 1. <hi>Herbert</hi> abbot of <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster,</hi> by permiſſion of <hi>Gylbert</hi> byſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and by conſent of the conuent, graunted to 3. Maides the Hermitage there which one <hi>Gorbone</hi> builded, with all the lande of that place.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Kingesburie,</hi> E. 12.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13561:20"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13561:21"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of London</figDesc>
                     <head>LONDON</head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>coats of arms</figDesc>
                        <p>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                                    <desc>••••</desc>
                                 </gap>ers</item>
                              <item>Grocers</item>
                              <item>Drapers.</item>
                              <item>Fiſhmongers</item>
                              <item>Goldſmiths.</item>
                              <item>Skinners.</item>
                              <item>Merchantaylors</item>
                              <item>Haberdaſhers</item>
                              <item>Salters.</item>
                              <item>Ironmongers</item>
                              <item>Vintners.</item>
                              <item>Clothworkers</item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                     </figure>
                     <byline>Pieter Vanden Keere fecit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1593.</byline>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> one of the for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> 12 Compaines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Lo. Mayor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Cyte comenly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>a. Buſhops gate ſtreete.</item>
                           <item>b. Papie.</item>
                           <item>c. Alballowes in the wall.</item>
                           <item>d. S Taphyns.</item>
                           <item>e. Sylner ſheete.</item>
                           <item>f. Aldermanburye.</item>
                           <item>g. Barbican.</item>
                           <item>h Aldeſgate ſtreete.</item>
                           <item>i Charterhowſe.</item>
                           <item>k Holborne Conduct.</item>
                           <item>l. Chauncery lane.</item>
                           <item>m. Temple barr.</item>
                           <item>n. Hobourn.</item>
                           <item>o. Grayes Inn lane</item>
                           <item>p. S Androwes.</item>
                           <item>q. Newgate.</item>
                           <item>r. S. Iones.</item>
                           <item>ſ. S Nic ſhambels.</item>
                           <item>t. Cheap ſyde.</item>
                           <item>u. Bucklers bury</item>
                           <item>w. Brodeſtreele.</item>
                           <item>x. The ſtockes.</item>
                           <item>y. The Exchanng</item>
                           <item>z. Cornehill</item>
                           <item>2. Colmanſtreete.</item>
                           <item>3. Baſſings hall.</item>
                           <item>4. Honnſditche.</item>
                           <item>5. Leadon hall.</item>
                           <item>6. Gratious ſtreete.</item>
                           <item>7. Heneage houſe.</item>
                           <item>8. Fancſhurche.</item>
                           <item>9. Marke lane.</item>
                           <item>10. Minchyn lane.</item>
                           <item>11. Paules.</item>
                           <item>12. Eaſteheape.</item>
                           <item>13. Eleeſtreete</item>
                           <item>14. Fetier lane.</item>
                           <item>15. S. Dunſhous.</item>
                           <item>16. Themes ſh treete</item>
                           <item>17. Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don ſtone.</item>
                           <item>18. Olde Baylye.</item>
                           <item>19. Clerkenwell.</item>
                           <item>20. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ncheſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </item>
                           <item>21. Battle hriage</item>
                           <item>22. Bermodſoy ſtreete</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ioannes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> deſcripſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13561:21"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13561:22"/>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:13561:22"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Kenton,</hi> E. 10.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Knightesbridge,</hi> G. 18.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Denſington,</hi> G. 16.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Kingstonwyke,</hi> K. 14. It is a Hamlet neere <hi>Kingstone</hi> vpon <hi>Thamis,</hi> ſtanding in MYDDLESEX, and is ſo called,<note place="margin">Wike whence deriued.</note> for that it is a rowe of houſes leading into <hi>Kingstone,</hi> which rowe of houſes in Lattine is called <hi>Vicus,</hi> in our toong <hi>Vyke</hi> or <hi>Wyke,</hi> of the Saxons pyc. <hi>Vadianus</hi> an excellent Geographer,<note place="margin">Vadian Coſme.</note> ſaith that <hi>Vicus in opido via est domorum ſeriem complexa, Vike</hi> is a way or paſſage in a towne being orderly compact of houſes, which we alſo cala ſtreete. In <hi>Rome</hi> are divers of theſe ſtreetes, as <hi>Vicus affricus, Vicus ciprius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Vicus celera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Vicus ſceleratus Roma.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Kenton,</hi> K. 10.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>L.</head>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>London,</hi> F. 20. the moſt famous Citie in all <hi>Brytaine,</hi> which <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> vpon the Proverbe <hi>Rhodii ſacrificium,</hi> ſaith, is deducted of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> a citie of the Ile of <hi>Rhodes, Stephanus</hi> calleth it <hi>Lyndonium,</hi> the Saxons Londenscaster, Londenbiryg Londenƿyc, <hi>Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey, Cornelius Tacitus,</hi> and <hi>Antonius, Londiniu,</hi> and <hi>Longidinium, Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus Londinum:</hi> the Welchmen <hi>Lundayne,</hi> we call it <hi>London: Ieffrey</hi> of <hi>Monmouth, Troia nova,</hi> or <hi>Ternouantum</hi> Newe Troy; ſome call it <hi>Luddes-Towne</hi> of <hi>Ludde</hi> the eldeſt ſonne of <hi>Helie: Leland</hi> taketh it to be <hi>Trenouans,</hi> new Towne, for that in the britiſh toong <hi>Tre</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth a towne: M. <hi>Camden</hi> ſeemeth, in ſome ſort, to yeelde that it ſhould be called <hi>London</hi> of the Britiſh word <hi>Lhwn,</hi> which ſignifieth a woode, or elſe he will haue it <hi>London</hi> or <hi>Londinum</hi> of the Britiſh word <hi>Lhong,</hi> which ſignifieth ſhips or ſhipping, in regarde that our <hi>Thamis</hi> yeeldeth ſuch apt acceſſe for ſhips euen to the citie.</p>
                     <p>There is great varietie among writers, who firſt founded this Citie: Some will haue <hi>Brute</hi> the Troian to be firſt builder of it, but <hi>Brute,</hi> and his hiſtorie, is meerely reiected of manie in our daies. It was reedefied by <hi>Lud,</hi> in the yeere of the worlds creation 5131.<note place="margin">Bale.</note> who builded the wals about it, and erected <hi>Ludgate,</hi> who alſo chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the name of <hi>Trenouant</hi> into <hi>Luddeſtowne,</hi> now <hi>London,</hi> for which alteration of <hi>Troye</hi> to <hi>Luddestowne,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gildas. Galfrid.</hi> Monuni. ponticus Brit. hist. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                        </note> great contention aroſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Britons,</hi> as reporteth <hi>Gildas</hi> and others. But our late writers will not conſent heereunto: Inſomuch as this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Citie lacketh the truth of it foundation, as many other famous monuments alſo do. But it nowe reteineth the name of <hi>London,</hi> famous through the whole worlde. A Citie of great Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, populous, rich, and beautifull;</p>
                     <p>This Citie was burned and greatly waſted by the hoſt of the pagan <hi>Danes,</hi> in the time of king <hi>Alphred,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Greg. in past. <hi>London</hi> burned.</note> as reporteth <hi>Gregory</hi> in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13561:23"/>his Paſtorale about the yeere of Chriſt 872.<note place="margin">London reede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</note> This <hi>Alphred</hi> about the yeere 886. in the 35. yeere of his natiuitie reedefied this Citie, beautifieng the ſame with faire buildings, and committed the cuſtody thereof to <hi>Alphred</hi> Earle of <hi>Mercia,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Fabyan.</note> as the ſame <hi>Gregorie</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth.</p>
                     <p>A great part of <hi>London</hi> was againe burned about the yeere of Chriſt 981. At what time it had moſt buildings, from <hi>Ludgate</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Westminſter,</hi> and little, where the heart of the Citie nowe is, but buildings ſcattered heere and there out of forme and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: So that it ſeemed inferior to diuers other Cities of this land, as <hi>Lincolne, Canterbury, Yorke</hi> and others, as by the role of <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> appeereth. But after the conqueſt it was reedefied, and by the conquerour greatly increaſed, So that by degrees it is become a moſt ample and ſtately Citie, far excelling all other in this land.</p>
                     <p>This Citie was (before the conqueſt) made by <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy</hi>) gouerned by <hi>Portreeues,</hi> called of the Saxons por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tgerefas whom the Germans call <hi>Burgreues,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The gouernement of <hi>London.</hi>
                        </note> which gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt altered, and appoimed two baylifes. Who in the time of King <hi>Iohn</hi> and by his command were diſcharged, for a time, by 35. elders or heads of the Citie, for a contempt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King. But they were not long in diſgrace, but through their ſubmiſſion and the diſcreete handling of the matter by theſe 35. heads or elders of the Citie, the King not onely forgaue the baylifes, but granted vnto the Citie by his letters pattents, that they ſhould yeerely chooſe vnto the mſelues, a Ma yor which vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally is of one of the 12. companies, mentioned in the Map of the Citie, and two Shirifes who haue beene accuſtomed to take their oth vpon Saint <hi>Mathewes</hi> day, nine daies befor Michelmas, and vpon Michelmas day to take their charge, but it is now otherwiſe. The firſt Mayor was choſen in the tenth yeere of King <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The first Mayor of <hi>Lodnon.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 1209. Euery May or was wont to be preſented to the King where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he was in <hi>England,</hi> vntill <hi>Henrie</hi> the thirds time, about <hi>Anno</hi> 1242. and before the King to be ſworne; after that it was referred to the Barons of the <hi>Exchequere,</hi> and ſo continueth to this day. Sir <hi>Iohn Allin</hi> knight, twice Mayor of London gaue a coller of gold to be ſucceſſiuely worne by the Mayor <hi>Anno</hi> 1544. In the time of <hi>H.</hi> 3. alſo the Aldermen of the Citie were or deined,<note place="margin">Alcermen of <hi>London.</hi>
                        </note> who tooke rule of the particuler wardes thereof, 25. in number, and theſe Aldermen were yeerely changed as are the Shirifes, but now it is otherwiſe, which wardes and the pariſhes in them are theſe.</p>
                     <list>
                        <head>Tower ward.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Olafe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Alhallowes</hi> at Berking.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Dunstane.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:13561:23"/>
                        <head>Billingſgate warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Botolph.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>George</hi> in pudding lane:</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Androw</hi> in Eaſtcheape.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Margaret Pattens.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mary hill.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Dowgate warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Laurance Pountney.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Alhallowes</hi> the more.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Alhallowes</hi> the leſſe.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Bridgeſtreete warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Bennet</hi> of grace Church.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Leonard</hi> in Eaſtcheape.</item>
                        <item>
                           <list>
                              <head>Newfiſhstreete.</head>
                              <item>S. <hi>Margaret</hi> in Bridgeſtreete.</item>
                              <item>S. <hi>Magnes</hi> in Bridgeſtreete.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Walbrooke warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in Walbrooke.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mary B.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Swythyn</hi> in Candlewikeſtreet.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Stephen</hi> in Walbrooke.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mary Woulchurch</hi> in the Poultrie.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Syth</hi> in Bucklersbury.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Candlewike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreete warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Martyn Orgor.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Clement.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Michael</hi> in Croked lane.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mary Abchurch.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Langburne warde.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Alhallowes Stains</hi> in Lumbareſtreet.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Gabriell.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Dionis</hi> in Fanchurch ſtreete.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Edmond.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Nicholas Acon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mary Wolnoth</hi> in Lumbare ſtreete.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Algate ward.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Androwes Vnderſhaft.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Katherines</hi> by Chriſteschurch.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Katherin Colman.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Port Sowkin warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Botolph</hi> without Algate.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Lymeſtreete warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mary Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <pb n="30" facs="tcp:13561:24"/>
                        <head>Buſhopes gate warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Botolph</hi> at the gate.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Alborgth.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Alhallowes</hi> within S. <hi>Helines.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Cornehill warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Michaell.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Peter.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Brodeſtreete warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Martyn Outwich.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Bennet Finck.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Bartholmew</hi> the little.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Christopher.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Peter</hi> the poore.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Alhallowes</hi> on the wall.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Colman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet ward.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Sthephen.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Olafe</hi> in the Iurie.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Margares</hi> in Lothburie.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Cheape warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Laurence</hi> in the Iurie.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Marie Bow.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Alhallowes</hi> in hony lane.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Colchurch.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Myldreds</hi> in the Pultrie.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Bennes Shorehog.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Martyn Poniers.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Martyn</hi> in Iremonger lane.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Maryes.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <item>S. <hi>Marie</hi> or <hi>Aldermarie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Anceline.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Pancras.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Queenehyth warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mychaell.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mary Somerſet.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mary Mowthaw.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Nicholas Olafe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Nicholas</hi> colde Abbey.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Peter.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Bredſtreete warde.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Alhallowes</hi> in Bredſtreete.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Myldred.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mathie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Io. Euangelist.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Augustine</hi> at Paules gate.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="31" facs="tcp:13561:24"/>S. <hi>Margaret Moyſes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Botolph.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Margaret</hi> in Friday ſtreete.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Vintry warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Martyn.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mychaell Colledge.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Thomas Apoſtole.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Iames</hi> on Garlikehyth.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Trinitie</hi> in Knightriderſtreete.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Beynerdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>andrew.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Bennet.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>George.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mary Magdelene</hi> in old fiſhſtreete.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>The warde of Farringdon <hi>infrá.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Euan.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Nùholas</hi> in the Fleſhſhambles.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Faithes</hi> in Paules.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Martyn</hi> within Ludgate.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mychaell</hi> at <hi>Querns.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Fauster</hi> in Fauſter lane.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Peter</hi> at the croſſe of Cheape.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Gregory</hi> in Paules Churchyarde.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Genyn</hi> within S. Martin <hi>le graunde.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>The warde of Farringdon <hi>extra.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Dunſtane.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Bride.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Androw</hi> in Holborne.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Pulcher</hi> without Newgate.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>aldreſgate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Botolph</hi> without Aldreſgate.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Anne.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Iohn Zacharie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Leonard</hi> in Fauſter lane.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Marie Staining.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mathew</hi> in ſiluer ſtreete.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Baſſinghall warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mychaell.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Creplegate warde.</head>
                        <item>S. <hi>Mary Magdelene.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Marie</hi> in Aldermanburie.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Michaell</hi> in Hogginlane.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Albons</hi> in Woodſtreete.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Elſinge</hi> ſpittle now a pariſh church.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="32" facs="tcp:13561:25"/>S. <hi>Olafe</hi> in Syluerſtreete.</item>
                        <item>S. <hi>Gyles</hi> without the gate.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <item>Wardes 25.</item>
                        <item>Pariſhes. 113.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>Other Churches there are within this Citie not mentioned in the wardes, nor vſed as pariſh Churches: whereof the firſt is <hi>Paules,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Paules <hi>buylded.</hi>
                        </note> a moſt ſtately temple, builded by <hi>Ethelbert</hi> king of <hi>Kent, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> 610. who conſecrated the ſame vnto S. <hi>Paule.</hi> It was afterward augmented by <hi>Mauricius</hi> biſhop of <hi>London, anno</hi> 1107. <hi>Henry Lacy</hi> Earle of Lincolne, builded the ſouth croſſe Ile, &amp; was there buried <hi>anno</hi> 1310. It is a Cathedrall Chruch the biſhops Sea of <hi>London;</hi> ſometime the archbiſhops Sea, but remooued thence to <hi>Caunter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie,</hi> by the meanes of S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> at the requeſt of the Citizens of <hi>Caunterbury.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Paules <hi>ſteeple.</hi>
                        </note> In the middell of this famous temple, is a Tower moſt artificially raiſed vpon ſtrong pillers, verie admirable to be conſidered, for that the foundation of the ſame maine Tower can not be deſerned in the bodie of the Church, and yet aſcendeth in great altitude, as it were in the center of the church, not (without curious view) to be ſeene, howe it is ſupported: vpon this Tower was raiſed a <hi>Piramis</hi> or (as we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly terme it) as Steeple, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with lead, which is ſaide to haue beene in altitude equall with the church in longitude, the height therof is recorded to be 534. foote from the ground: which ſtately <hi>piramis</hi> or ſteeple was thrice conſumed with fire:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Paules</hi> ſteeple burned three times.</note> firſt in the yeere of Chriſt 1087. which was not long after newlie erected: and burned againe <hi>anno</hi> 1444. after that raiſed and againe conſumed with fire, by vnknowne meanes (the iudgement of God inkindling it) in the yeere of Chriſt 1561. to the terror of the whole Citie: remaining as yet wihtout that ſtately ornament.</p>
                     <p>There lieth buried <hi>Sebba</hi> king of the eaſt Saxons who died <hi>anno domini</hi> 633. in a coffin of marble with couer of the ſame, his armes theſe.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>There alſo lieth buried <hi>Etheldred</hi> king of <hi>England,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">King <hi>Etheldred</hi> burted.</note> the ſonne of <hi>Edgar</hi> who died <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no domini</hi> 1017. in a coffin of marble with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of the ſame.</p>
                     <p>There lieth alſo <hi>Iohn</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Plantaginet</hi> in a ſtately monument,<note place="margin">10. Plantaginet <hi>buried.</hi>
                        </note> artificially raiſed of white free ſtone, whoſe ſtile is thus there recorded.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Illustriſſimus iacet hic,</hi> Iohannes <hi>cognomento</hi> Plantaginet, <hi>Rex</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiliae, <hi>&amp;</hi> Legionis, <hi>Dux</hi> Lancaſtrie, <hi>Comes</hi> Richmondiae Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtriae, Lincolnie <hi>&amp;</hi> Derbiae, <hi>locum tenens</hi> Aquitaniae, <hi>magnus
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13561:25"/>Seneſcallus</hi> Angliae <hi>obiit anno</hi> 22. Ric. 2. <hi>Annoque Domini</hi> 1399.</p>
                     <p>Alſo there was a Church at the <hi>Crotched fryars</hi> now conuerted to other vſe.</p>
                     <p>A Church at <hi>Auguſtine friars</hi> founded by <hi>Humfrey Bohune</hi> E. of H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tford,<note place="margin">1253.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>A Church called <hi>Tho.</hi> of <hi>Acris</hi> neer the great conduct in <hi>Cheape</hi> founded by <hi>Thomas fitz-Theobald</hi> in the time of H. 2. who gaue the ſame Church to the <hi>Mercers</hi> for a peece of money,<note place="margin">Rec. E. 3. <hi>Anno</hi> 19.</note> at the ſuite of ſir <hi>Richard Greſham</hi> knight, and is now vſed for the <hi>Mercers hall.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Temple</hi> within <hi>Temple barre,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The Temple.</note> whoſe founder is not certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recorded, yet ſome hold it to be that which was called <hi>Templum pacis</hi> or <hi>Concordiae,</hi> builded by <hi>Dunwallo Mulmutius,</hi> about the yeer of the worldes creation 4748. and therein was buried the ſame <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutius</hi> and alſo <hi>Gorbomanus</hi> and others.<note place="margin">Galfr. Mon.</note> But ſome take the <hi>Temple</hi> of peace to be that which is now <hi>Blackwell-hall.</hi> There are in this <hi>Temple,</hi> many very auncient monuments of famous men, ſhaped in Marble armed, their legges croſſe, whoſe names are not to be gathered, by any inſcription, for that, time hath worne it out. The form of this <hi>Temple,</hi> in the weſt, is made circuler, loftely raiſed with Marble pillers, ſet alſo circule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ly, ſo that it ſerueth, the ſtudents of the houſe for a walke moſt neceſſarie, &amp; that, for a multitude with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſturbance of one by the other, by reuerting. Some ſay it was founded by the kings templers which were in <hi>England</hi> about the yeere of Chriſt 1185. but it ſeemeth that this <hi>Temple</hi> is farre more auncient.</p>
                     <p>There was annexed vnto the <hi>Stilliarde</hi> an auncient Church called the <hi>Temple</hi> alſo, and after the diſſolution thereof,<note place="margin">A temple neere the Stilliarde.</note> it was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the ſtudents of the Law, bearing the name of <hi>White hall,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">White hall.</note> which belike in regard of the diſtance from the other houſes of Law, it was at the length neglected and forſaken, which houſe ſeemeth to be of the number of the houſes of Chauncery, in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, when Maſter <hi>Forteſcue</hi> compiled his booke of the Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> wherein he affirmeth that there were in, and neere <hi>London,</hi> ten Innes of Chauncery, now but eight, in which number of ten, was accompted this <hi>White hall,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Strand</hi> Inne, which ſtood within the compaſſe of <hi>Somerſet houſe</hi> neere the <hi>Strand.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Stilliarde</hi> (called of the <hi>Gothes</hi> the <hi>Haunſe</hi>) ſignifieth a place of meeting of the people,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Stilliarde</hi> why ſo called.</note> and eſpecially the Marchants of many Countries, and Cities: as of <hi>England, France, Denmarke, Muſcouie, Brabant, Flaunders,</hi> and many other, where they enterchanged Marchandize by the ſundry priueleges and freedomes of many Kings, Dukes, and Princes, which of late yeeres hath by little and little diſcontinued. It is not againſt reaſon, to thinke that theſe auncient <hi>Temples</hi> were erected by the <hi>Pagans</hi> wherein they offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13561:26"/>ſacrifices to their countrey gods.<note place="margin">Galfr. Mon.</note> For it appeareth by the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie of <hi>Ieffery</hi> of <hi>Monmoth</hi> that while <hi>C. Alectus</hi> Captaine of the Romaine hoſt, was thus buſied in his Pagan ſacrifice M. <hi>Aur. Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clepiodotus</hi> duke of <hi>Cornewall</hi> whom the <hi>Britons</hi> had elected to be their King, came to <hi>London,</hi> and beſieged, and entred it; betweene whom was a hard conflict and <hi>Asclepiodotus</hi> vanquiſhed the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes</hi> and after beſet <hi>Gallus</hi> another Captaine of the <hi>Romanes</hi> who remained in the citie, and ouercame him, who with his <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes</hi> being put to the ſworde the chiefe Captaine <hi>Gallus</hi> was caſt into a brooke, which then, and long ſince, ran through the Citie, whereof it is ſuppoſed to be called of the auncient <hi>Britons,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Walbrooke.</note> 
                        <hi>Nant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall</hi> of the <hi>Saxons</hi> galenbourne, and of vs at this day <hi>Wallbrooke,</hi> which runneth neere <hi>London ſtone</hi> which ſtone is neere in the mid way betweene <hi>Ludd gate</hi> and the Tower poſterne gate.</p>
                     <p>There are about this Citie 11. Gates of name, whereof foure are towardes the north, as <hi>Alderſgate</hi> ſuppoſed to be ſo called of the <hi>Alders</hi> which grew there, and ſome holde it to take name of <hi>Aldricius</hi> the <hi>Saxon,</hi> it may be ſo called of the antiquitie thereof, <hi>Aldestgate</hi> in the comparatiue degree as <hi>Aldgate, Newgate,</hi> in the poſitiue. <hi>Creplegat,</hi> So called for that it was the houſe for halt and lame, a hoſpitall for creeples and impotent people, it hath beene of late reedified by <hi>Edmond Thaa</hi> in the yeere of Chriſt 1490. <hi>Moregate</hi> ſo called for that it was the paſſage into a mooriſh, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, or watrie ground, which is called <hi>Moore fielde,</hi> though now brought to be more firme, by the induſtry and charge of a Mayor of <hi>London</hi> about 180. yeeres paſt. <hi>Buſhopes gate</hi> builded by certaine Marchantes which traueled into <hi>Germaine</hi> belonging to the olde Haunce: But it ſeemeth by the adiunct that it ſhould be builded by a Buſhop.</p>
                     <p>There are vpon the <hi>Thamis</hi> three gates, though two of them ſeeme rather portes or hauens for ſhipes and boates then gates for paſſage, onely the <hi>Bridge gate</hi> is a thorough fare, or paſſage by horſe and foote, but <hi>Billingſgate</hi> is a harbor or kaye for ſhipping, yet hath the name of a gate, for that it was erected firſt like a gate,<note place="margin">Galfr. Mon.</note> by <hi>Bellinus,</hi> and of him called <hi>Bellines gate,</hi> in the top whereof he cauſed to be erected a <hi>Pyramis</hi> and on the top of it a veſſell of ſtone, wherein he appointed the aſhes of his brent body to be put after his death. There is alſo <hi>Dowgate</hi> or <hi>Dourgate</hi> that is <hi>Watergate</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>On the eaſt is one gate called <hi>Aldegate,</hi> ſo called of the antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thereof, as M. <hi>Camden</hi> and others ſuppoſe.</p>
                     <p>On the weſt are two gates <hi>Luddgate</hi> or <hi>Luddeſgate,</hi> of LVDD the ſuppoſed founder, who is ſaide to lie interredin the Church of S. <hi>Martins</hi> within the gate.<note place="margin">Anno ante Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum <hi>66.</hi>
                        </note> This gate was of late yeeres newly buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and made a moſt ſtately gate about the yeere of Chriſt, 1586. to the great charge of the Citie.<note place="margin">Galfr. Mon.</note> 
                        <hi>Ieffrey</hi> of <hi>Monmouth</hi> reporteth,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13561:26"/>that the image of CADWALLO was in braſſe artificially fixed on a braſen horſe, ſet on the toppe of this gate,<note place="margin">Cadwallo <hi>buried</hi>
                        </note> in token of a victorie had againſt the <hi>Saxom:</hi> whoſe body was alſo buried in S. <hi>Martynes</hi> church within the gate.</p>
                     <p>There was betweene <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Southwarke</hi> long time paſſage by ferrie vntill the Citizens cauſed a bridge of woode to be erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:<note place="margin">Lonlon bridge.</note> after that, in the time of R 1 c. 2. <hi>anno</hi> 1176. they beganne to build a bridge of ſtone, which in the time of king IOHN they moſt artificially finiſhed, <hi>anno</hi> 1209. contriuing it of 20. at ches, and in the midſt a drawe bridge, and vppon the ſame bridge on either ſide, the houſes ſo artificially combined, that the whole bridge ſeemeth not onely a mayne and faire ſtreete, but men ſeeme to paſſe vnder a continuall roofe; the bridge is in height 60. foote, in bredth 30. foote, the arches are in ſunder 20. foote, there are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the north arch of this bridge, moſt artificially erected certain wheeles or tide myles, which riſe and fall according to the ebs &amp; flouds, and they raiſe the water by pypes and counductes ſo high that it ſerueth ſuch citizens houſes in all places of <hi>London,</hi> as will beſtow charge towarde the conducting thereof: The buildings vppon this bridge, on either ſide were conſumed with fire An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 1208.<note place="margin">Pollid. Virg.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>There is neere the three Cranes, a Church called now S. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaels,</hi> ſometime <hi>Whittingdon Colledge</hi> founded by ſir <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingdon,</hi> ſometime Mayor of <hi>London.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There was in that place which is nowe knowne by the name of <hi>Blacke-fryers,</hi> an auncient and ſtrong caſtle, which was called <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latyne,</hi> burned in the time of WILLIAM the <hi>Conquerour:</hi> in the place of which caſtle are at this day erected many faire &amp; beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full buildings, and here and there the auncient wals and build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings as yet appeare.</p>
                     <p>On the eaſt part of the Citie, is a moſt famous and ſtrong Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, called the <hi>Tower of London,</hi> the maine tower whereof, ſome ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be builded by IVLIVS CAESAR. It is ſtrong and ample, well walled and trenched about, beautified with ſundrie build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, ſemblable to a little towne.</p>
                     <p>There is in <hi>Cornehill</hi> a moſt famous monument, ſtately erected by ſir <hi>thomas Greſham</hi> knight, who named it the <hi>Burſe,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The Royall Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change.</note> whereunto afterwarde Queene ELIZABETH gaue the name of <hi>Royall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change;</hi> It is the place of the place of the publike meeting of Marchaunts, aſwell Engliſh as foraine, wherunto twice euery day they dulie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort, the form of the building is quadrate, with walks round the mayne building ſupported with pillers of marble, ouer which walkes is a place for the ſale of all kinde of wares, richly ſtored with varietie of all ſorts. It was builded about the yeere 1568.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Leadenhall</hi> neere <hi>Cornhill</hi> was builded by one <hi>Sunken Eyre,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Leaden hall.</note> about
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13561:27"/>
                        <hi>anno</hi> 1444. a place of prouiſion, or ſtore houſe for releefe for the poore in time of dearth.</p>
                     <p>Manie things might be ſpoken of this famous Citie which would too far exceede my purpoſe.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>The</hi> Longitude <hi>and</hi> Latitude <hi>of</hi> London.</note> It hath latitude 52. degrees, &amp; longitude 19. degrees 15. minuts. It is moſt ſweetely ſeituate vpon the <hi>Thamis,</hi> ſerued with all kinde of neceſſaries moſt commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſſie. The aire healthfull, it is populous, rich and beautifull, be it alſo faithfull, louing and thankfull.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lodghill</hi> D. 16. a hill or fort in <hi>Harneſey</hi> or <hi>Horneſey</hi> parke, and is called <hi>Lodghill,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Lodghill ſometime a fors.</note> for that thereon ſometime ſtoode a lodge, when the parke was repleniſhed with Deare, but it ſeemeth by the foundation that it was rather a caſtle, then a lodge, for the hill is at this day trenched with two deepe ditches, now olde and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growne with buſhes: the rubble thereof, as bricke, tile, and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſlate, are in heapes yet to be ſeene, which ruines are of great antiquity, as may appeere by the okes, at this day ſtanding (aboue 100. yeeres grouth,) vpon the very foundation of the building. It did belong to the biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> at which place haue beene dated diuers cuidences, ſome of which remaine yet in the biſhops regeſtrie (as is ſaid.)</p>
                     <p>This parke hath beene repleniſhed with ſtately timber trees in great aboundance, now with the famous fort fallen to the ground as the Poet ſaith,
<q>
                           <l>Euum cuncta rapit furtiuáque temporamutant.</l>
                           <l>Naturam, fortem, Nominaque &amp; faciem.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>** <hi>Ludraues,</hi> b. 18. a faire houſe ſcytuate in a valley neere <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeylde</hi> chace, belonging vnto</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lymehouſe,</hi> G. 22.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lalam,</hi> I. 8.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Littleton</hi> I. 8. in regard of the quantitie it may be called <hi>Linle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>towne.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Linluon.</note>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>M.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>More hall,</hi> E. 4.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mylhill,</hi> D. 14.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Muſwell hill,</hi> D. 18. called alſo <hi>Pinſenall hill:</hi> there was a chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſometime bearing the name of our Ladie of <hi>Muſwell:</hi> where now alderman <hi>Roe</hi> hath erected a proper houſe, the place taketh name of the Well and of the hill, <hi>Mouſewell hill,</hi> for there is on the hil a ſpring of faire water, which is now within the compas of the houſe.<note place="margin">The Ladie of Muſwell.</note> There was ſometime an image of the ladie of <hi>Muſwell,</hi> whereunto was a continuall reſort, in the way of pylgrimage, growing as is (though as I take it) fabulouſlie reported, in regard of a great cure which was performed by this water, vpon a king
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13561:27"/>of <hi>Seats,</hi> who being ſtrangely diſeaſed, was by ſome deuine intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, aduiſed to take the water of a Well in <hi>England,</hi> called <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> which after long ſcrutation, and inquiſition, this Well was found and performed the cure; abſolutely to denie the cure I dare not, for that the high God hath giuen vertue vnto waters, to heale infirmities, as may appeere by the cure of <hi>Naaman</hi> the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, by waſhing himſelfe ſeauen times in <hi>Iordan,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. King. 1.14. Iohn 5.2.</note> and by the poole <hi>Betheſda,</hi> which healed the next that ſtepped thereinto, after the water was mooued by the angell.</item>
                  <item>* <hi>Mockings,</hi> called alſo the mannor of <hi>Mockings,</hi> D. 22. an aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent houſe, of the Lord <hi>Comptons,</hi> moated about.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Morehatch,</hi> A. 20. a hamlet of <hi>Enfeylde.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Marybone,</hi> F. 18.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Meerstreete,</hi> F. 22. a member of <hi>Hackney.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>N.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Northend,</hi> C. 16. a hamlet of <hi>Finchley.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>** <hi>Newington,</hi> E. 20. there, the Earle of <hi>Oxforde</hi> is ſometime re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, in a very proper houſe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Neeſdon,</hi> or <hi>Neuſdon,</hi> E. 14. a houſe ſometime the <hi>Elringtons. Northolt lodge,</hi> F. 6.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Northolt,</hi> F. 8. it ſoundeth <hi>Northwood,</hi> for <hi>hols</hi> in the Germayne toung ſignifieth wood.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Norwood,</hi> or <hi>Northwood,</hi> F. 8.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Norcote,</hi> or <hi>Northcote,</hi> G. 8.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>O.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Olde forde,</hi> F. 22. a village taking name of the forde or paſſage at that place, ouer the riuer <hi>Lea</hi> in time paſt.</item>
                  <item>* <hi>Osterley,</hi> or <hi>Oyſterley,</hi> G. 10. the houſe nowe of the ladie <hi>Greſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Osterley builded.</note> a faire and ſtately building of bricke, erected by ſir <hi>Thomas Greſham</hi> knight, Citizen and Marchant aduenturer of <hi>London,</hi> and finiſhed about <hi>anno</hi> 1577. It ſtandeth in a parke by him alſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paled, well wooded, and garniſhed with manie faire ponds, which affoorded not onely fiſh, and fowle, as ſwanes, and other water foule: but alſo great vſe for milles, as paper milles, oyle milles, and corne milles, all which are now decaied (a corne mill excepted.) In the ſame parke was a verie faire Heronrie, for the increaſe &amp; preſeruation whereof, ſundrie allurements were deuiſed and ſet vp fallen all to ruine.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>P.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Prnner,</hi> E. 8.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:13561:28"/>* <hi>Pymmes,</hi> C. 20. a proper little houſe of the right Honorable Lord <hi>Burghley,</hi> Lord high <hi>Treaſurer</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ponder sen,</hi> B. 20. a hamlet of <hi>Enfeylds.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Potters bar,</hi> A. 16.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Preston,</hi> E. 12.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Peryuale,</hi> or <hi>Pureuale,</hi> F. 10. of this place is ſpoken before in the nature of the ſoyle of MYDDLESEX.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Paddington,</hi> F. 16.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Paddingwyke,</hi> G. 14. for the the ſignification of Wyke ſee <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonwyke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pancras Church,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pancras Church very auncient. F. 20.</note> ſtandeth all alone as vtterly forſaken, old and wetherbeaten, which for the antiquitie therof, it is thought not to yeeld to <hi>Paules</hi> in <hi>London:</hi> about this Church haue bin ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie buildings, now decaied, leauing poore <hi>Pancras</hi> without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie or comfort: yet it is now and then viſited with <hi>Kentiſh towne</hi> and <hi>Highgate,</hi> which are members therof: but they ſeldome come there, for that they haue chappels of eaſe within themſelues, but when there is a corps to be interred, they are forced to leaue the ſame in this forſaken church or churchyard, where (no doubt) it reſteth as ſecure againſt the day of reſurrection as if it laie in ſtately <hi>Paules.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pancras</hi> as deſſolate as it ſtandeth is not forſaken of all: apre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brend of <hi>Paules</hi> accepeth it in right of his office.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Parſons greene,</hi> H. 16.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>R.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Riſelip</hi> E. 16.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>S.</head>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Syon.</hi> H. 12. was built by HENRIE the 5. ſometimes a houſe of munkes,<note place="margin">Syon builded.</note> but this king expelled them, and int heir place eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed certaine virgins of <hi>Bridgets</hi> order; and appointed of them ſo many with prieſts and lay brethren, as were equall with the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Apoſtles and Diſciples of Chriſt, namelie of virgines 60. prieſts 13. deanes, 4. lay brethren 8. which made 13. Apoſtles, and 72. Diſciples of Chriſt, vpon whome hauing beſtowed ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent reuenues for their maintenaunce, he made a lawe that they ſhould not accept of any other gift, but content themſelues with his contribution: and to beſtow on the poore whatſoeuer was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue that which might reaſonably ſuffice them.</p>
                     <p>It is now a houſe of hir Maieſties, ſtanding moſt pleaſantly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the riuer of <hi>Thamys.</hi> It was called <hi>Syon</hi> in remembrance of that hill in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which was called the <hi>Holy hill,</hi> the <hi>mount of the Lord,</hi>
                        <pb n="39" facs="tcp:13561:28"/>the <hi>Citie of Dauid, Mouns Syon.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>** <hi>Swakeleys,</hi> E. 6. ſometime a houſe of the <hi>Brockeyes,</hi> nowe fir <hi>Thomas Sherleyes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Stanmer great,</hi> D. 10.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Stanmer little,</hi> called alſo <hi>Whytechurch,</hi> D. 10.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>South mymmes.</hi> A. 14. there is a faire warren of conies of the Lo. <hi>Windſores.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Shackelwell,</hi> E. 22.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Shordich,</hi> F. 20.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Stretford on the bow,</hi> F. 24. the bridge ouer the riuer lea,<note place="margin">Ree. E. <hi>anno</hi> 22.</note> is the Bow, and thereof is called <hi>Stratford on the bow,</hi> neere it, is an olde church, founded by HEN. 2.</item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Stepney,</hi> or <hi>Stybenhyth,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Sir</hi> Henry Collet <hi>knight buried</hi>
                        </note> or <hi>Stibonbeath,</hi> F. 22. In the church thereof is buried ſir <hi>Henry Collet</hi> knight, twice Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> who was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>Iohn Collet,</hi> ſometime Deane of <hi>Paules,</hi> who alone builded <hi>Paules ſchoole,</hi> his armes theſe.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>There lyeth alſo the Lady <hi>Anne Wentworth</hi> wife to <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Wentworth,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Stepney. <hi>Lady</hi> Went<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth <hi>buried.</hi>
                        </note> and daughter to <hi>Henry Wentworth</hi> Eſquier. She died the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of Sept. 1571.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Spers</hi> knight ſometime Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the ſhipes to H. 8. Dame <hi>Margery,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Spert <hi>knight buried.</hi>
                        </note> Dame <hi>Anne,</hi> and Dame <hi>Mary</hi> his wiues, lie in the Chauncell there, he deceaſed <hi>Anno</hi> 1541.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:13561:29"/>In the north Ile of the ſame Church lyeth <hi>William Chaldnam</hi> eſquire,<note place="margin">William Chald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam <hi>Eſquire bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried.</hi>
                        </note> and <hi>Ioan</hi> his wife he died the 27. of Sept. <hi>Anno</hi> 1484.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Strond,</hi> called the <hi>Stroud</hi> H. 4. a hamlet neere <hi>Cheſwyke,</hi> and called the <hi>Strond,</hi> for that it bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth ſo neere the <hi>Thamys.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Southholt,</hi> ſignifieth Southwood, G. 8.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sypſon,</hi> G. 6.</item>
                  <item>** <hi>Stanwell</hi> H. 6. there was the auncient houſe of the <hi>Windſores.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Stanes Church,</hi> H. 6.</item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Stanes towne,</hi> I. 6. it is called in the <hi>Saxon</hi> toong. Stana. It ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon the <hi>Thamis,</hi> A market towne kept on the Friday week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is gouerned by two Cunſtables and foure Headborrowes: the towne is hir Maieſties lande, and the officers choſen by hir High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Steward. It ſtand eth from the church halfe a mile, and the Church ſtandeth vppon a little hill by it ſelfe, at if it were bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the towne.</p>
                     <p>Some affirme it to be called <hi>Stanes</hi> of the Stakes called <hi>Coway Stakes,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Coway ſtakes.</note> which were fixed in the <hi>Thamys</hi> by the Brytons, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent <hi>Iulius</hi> Caeſar, of paſſing his armie through the riuer. There is a towne called <hi>Stanes</hi> vpon the frontires of Italie in <hi>Tyroll,</hi> vpon the riuer <hi>Inn.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Bunn meadow.</note> There is a medow neere <hi>Stanes</hi> called <hi>Bunn meadow,</hi> where king IOHN had parley with his barons, and where were ſealed betweene them certeyne writings of truce.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sunburye</hi> K. 10. <hi>Nicaſius Yetſworth</hi> eſquire,<note place="margin">Nicaſius Yetſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth <hi>buried.</hi>
                        </note> ſometime ſecretarie of the French tounge to Queene ELIZABETH: And <hi>marie</hi> his wife, daughter to <hi>Ieames Bowſer</hi> eſquire, lie buried in the ſame church.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>There was alſo buried <hi>Daniell Rogers</hi> Eſquire ſometime Clerke of the Counſell to Queene ELIZABETH a man of excellent learning,<note place="margin">Daniel Rogers <hi>buried.</hi>
                        </note> and knowledge of toongs, and often imploid in Ambaſſage into <hi>Germainie, Denmarke, Low Countries, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Shepperton</hi> K. 8.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>T.</head>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Tottenham</hi> or <hi>Totheham</hi> D. 20. In which Church is buried <hi>George Heningham</hi> eſquire ſometime ſeruant, &amp; greatly fauored of K. <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi>
                        <pb n="41" facs="tcp:13561:29"/>the eight he founded there a little hoſpitall or almeſhouſe for three poore widowes.</p>
                     <p>* At this place the Lord <hi>Compton</hi> hath a proper ancient houſe.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tottenham highcroſſe</hi> D. 20. a hamlet belonging to <hi>Tottenham.</hi> and hath this adiunct <hi>Highcroſſe</hi> of a woodden croſſe, there loftly rayſed on a little mount of earth.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tottenham ſtreete</hi> C. 20.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Twyforde west</hi> E. 12. So called of two little brookes or fordes that paſſe neere it. It is a pariſh but it hath but one onely houſe thereunto belonging, which is one <hi>Iohn Lions</hi> Gentleman.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Twyforde east</hi> E. 12. belonging to a prebend of Paules.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Touen Court</hi> F. 18. belonging to a prebend of Paules.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Turnham greene</hi> G. 14.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thiſtle worth</hi> or <hi>Iſtleworth</hi> H. 12. a place ſcytuate vpon the <hi>Thamis,</hi> not far from whence, betweene it and <hi>Worton,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Copper and braſſe</note> is a copper and braſſe mill, where it is wrought out of the oare, melted and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. The oar, or earth, whereof it is contriued, is brought out of <hi>Sommerſet ſhire</hi> from <hi>Mendip hils,</hi> the moſt from <hi>Worley hill,</hi> manie artificiall deuiſes there are to be noted in the performance of the worke.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Twickenham</hi> I. 12 a pariſh ſeytuate vpon the <hi>Thamis.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Twickenham</hi> why ſo called.</note> So called either for that, at that place the <hi>Thames</hi> ſemeth to be deuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two Riuers by reaſon of the Iſlandes there, or elſe of the two brookes which neere the towne enter into the <hi>Thamis,</hi> for <hi>Twick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam</hi> is as much as <hi>Twynam, quaſi inter binos amnes ſitum,</hi> a place ſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate betweene two riuers.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tuddinton</hi> I. 12.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vxbridge</hi> or <hi>Woxbridge</hi> F. 4. a market towne vpon the edge of the ſhire, it is no pariſh of it ſelfe, but is amember of great <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingdon,</hi> but they haue a Chappell of eaſe buylt by <hi>Ro. Oliuer, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Mandin, Iohn Palmer,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iohn Barforde</hi> of the ſame towne. In the fix and twentith yeere of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt. The market is kept on the Thurſday. it is gouerned by two Baylifes, two Cunſtables, and foure Tythingmen called alſo Headborrowes, or as the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> call them Borhesealdors the chiefeſt or head pledges.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vxenden or Oxenden</hi> E. 12.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>W.</head>
                  <item>** <hi>Woodhall</hi> E. 8. the houſe of</item>
                  <item>* <hi>Wirehall</hi> E. 20. the houſe of <hi>Leeke</hi> Eſquire.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Waltham croſſe</hi> A. 20. the fartheſt part of this ſhire towardes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13561:30"/>the north, goeth to the Spittle there.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Whitweb</hi> A. 20.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Whetstone</hi> C. 16.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wilſdon</hi> of the <hi>Saxons</hi> ƿiuerlsdune E. 14.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wembly hill</hi> E. 12.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>West bourne</hi> F. 16. Weſt water.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Winchmore hill</hi> B. 20.</item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Westminster</hi> G. 18. Sometime called <hi>Thorney</hi> of the <hi>Saxons</hi> ðorney of ſome <hi>Dorney</hi> but (as I take it) <hi>D.</hi> is pronounced in ſteede of <hi>Th.</hi> as it is in many other ancient <hi>Saxon</hi> words,<note place="margin">Dorney for Thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</note> as Fader, Moder, Broder, for Father, Mother, Brother, which error ariſeth belike of the miſtaking of the capitall <hi>D.</hi> abreauiated thus Ð. which is as much as <hi>Th.</hi> and the little <hi>d.</hi> thus abreuiated ð. for <hi>Th.</hi> which abreuiations are often taken for the ſimple <hi>D.</hi> and d. by reaſon whereof it was called Dorney for Ðorney.</p>
                     <p>This <hi>Thorney</hi> now <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> was an Iſland inuironed with the <hi>Thamis,</hi> which deuided it ſelfe, and one braunch paſſed betweene <hi>Charing croſſe</hi> and <hi>Kings-ſtreete,</hi> throrowgh S. <hi>Ieames parke</hi> that now is,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Thorney</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time an Iſland.</note> including <hi>Tootehill,</hi> and was called <hi>Thorney</hi> Iſland, for that it was ouergrowen with bryers and thornes; which <hi>Thorney</hi> place was in the time of King LVCIVS (as Authors affirme) clenſed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yeere 186. which LVCIVS is ſaide to lay the firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the great Temple of S. <hi>Peters.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">S. Peters <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi>
                        </note> But Authors greatly vary touching the founders of the ſame Temple. Maſter <hi>Camden</hi> from <hi>Sulcardus</hi> reporteth that there was firſt a Temple in that place, dedicate to <hi>Apollo,</hi> which was ouerthrowne by an earth quake in the time of <hi>Antonius Pius.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Galfr. Mon.</note> It is not vnlike that ſuch an Idol Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was, for it is reported by auncient Authors, that the <hi>Troyno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes,</hi> or <hi>Trinobantes,</hi> did ſomtime ſacrifice Buls, Bullockes, Stags, and ſuch like to <hi>Diana Tauropolia</hi> whom the Gentiles called the Queene of <hi>Heauen.</hi> Of the ruynes of that Idoll Temple, It is ſaid that SEBERTVS King of the eaſt <hi>Saxons</hi> erected another Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for the ſeruice of the liuing God, and conſecrated the ſame to S. <hi>Peter,</hi> about the yeere of Chriſt 610. neere about the time of the building of <hi>Paules.</hi> Afterwardes it was deſtroyed by the <hi>Danes,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Math. Weſtm.</note> and <hi>Dunstan</hi> Buſhop of <hi>London,</hi> reedified it about the yeere of Chriſt 960. and made there a monaſterie for 12. Munckes. <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian</hi> ſaith it was builded by the means of ETHELBERT King of <hi>Kent,</hi> who alſo built <hi>Paules</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I haue heard that there are, or haue beene, records int he ſame Abbey, which declare that it was a Church before the <hi>Britons</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the faith, of Chriſt, which ſhould ſeeme to be that Idoll Church of <hi>Apollo</hi> before LVCIVS time.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>map of Westminster</figDesc>
                        <head>WESTMINSTER</head>
                     </figure>
                     <p>After <hi>Thorney,</hi> it became to be called <hi>Westminster,</hi> and that in regard of the ſcytuation of it weſt of <hi>London:</hi> for on the Tower hill was a monaſterie called <hi>Eastminster,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eaſtminſter.</note> of the eaſterly ſtanding thereof, which was called alſo <hi>New abbey,</hi> founded by EDW. 3. in the yeee 1359.</p>
                     <p>There are within this temple, diuers, and ſundrie, moſt rare and princely monuments: ſome of great antiquitie, ſome alſo of later times, increaſing dailie,<note place="margin">Edward confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor <hi>buried.</hi>
                        </note> among the reſt there lieth ED<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WARD called alſo the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> who laboured before in this famous worke, and cauſed his corps to be interred in the weſt part of the Church, which when HEN. 3. had altred, he cauſed the body of EDW. to be remooued, to the place where now it reſteth, in the eaſt part of the Church.</p>
                     <p>Alſo there lieth HEN. 3.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Henry</hi> the third buried. <hi>Tho. Walſing.</hi>
                        </note> the finiſher of this moſt famous worke, whoſe tombe is there in moſt kingly manner erected, by the dutifull endeuour and charge of EDW. 1. ſonne of the ſaid HEN. 3. and for that purpoſe, he brought Iaſper ſtones out of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> wherewith he beautified his fathers ſumptuous ſepulchre in <hi>anno</hi> 1280.</p>
                     <p>Manie other Kings and Queenes, and perſons of high ſtate, haue beene there buried, of whome the whole catalogue to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite would be tedious.</p>
                     <p>There is in this temple a ſtone, in forme of a chaire,<note place="margin">A ſtone chayre in <hi>S. Peters Church</hi>
                        </note> ſometime ſeruing, as the throne of the kings of <hi>Scots,</hi> and wherein they were crowned, which ſtone was brought out of <hi>Scone</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> by EDW. 1. ſonne to HEN. 3. about <hi>anno</hi> 1297. which ſtandeth not far from his fathers monument, had in no little price at this day.</p>
                     <p>There is adioining vnto this famous temple,<note place="margin">A chappell of <hi>H. 7.</hi>
                        </note> in the eaſt ende thereof, a chappell erected by HEN. 7. which in regarde of the beautie, and curious contriued worke thereof, is called of <hi>Lelande, Orbis miraculum:</hi> The wonder of the worlde. In this mirrour of art,<note place="margin">Orbis miraculum.</note> and archytect, are many rare and glorious monuments of Kings and Queenes,<note place="margin">H. 7. <hi>buried.</hi>
                        </note> among whom the famous founder HEN. 7. lieth vnder a moſt regall tombe, framed &amp; artificially formed of bras,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13561:33"/>richly guilded with pure gold.</p>
                     <p>Neere this chappell adioining vnto the <hi>Thamys,</hi> was an olde famous building,<note place="margin">Olde pallace.</note> called nowe the <hi>Olde pallace,</hi> which was conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with fire, in the time of EDW. the <hi>Confeſſor.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It was ſometime the pallace of king CANVTVS the <hi>Dane,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Olde pallace king <hi>Canutus</hi> houſe.</note> alſo king of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> and where he made his abode about the yeere of Chriſt, 1035. after his returne from <hi>Rome</hi> into <hi>Englande,</hi> who in regard of his quadruplicitie of kingdomes, eſteemed himſelfe, more than a man mortall: for his Scicophants had ſo bewitched him with their inchaunted flatteries, that he deemed himſelfe no leſſe then a God.<note place="margin">The pride of <hi>Cauntus.</hi>
                        </note> And in this proud conceit on a day he paſſed by the <hi>Thamys,</hi> which ran by that pallace, at the flowing of the tide, &amp; making ſtaie neere the water, the waues caſt foorth ſome part of the water towards him, this CANVTVS coniured the waues by his regall commaunde to proceede no farther: the <hi>Thamys</hi> vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with this newe God, held on it courſe, flowing as of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome it vſed to do, and refrained not to aſſayle him neere to the knees: whereat this high conceited man as one amazed, begon to tremble, ſtarting backe proteſting that hee was but a man, though a mightie king. And that he that gouerned thoſe waters, was onely worthie to be called a king, and all mortall men, moſt mightie kings, ought to ſubiect them vnto him. A woorthie note whereby is ſeene howe the almightie <hi>Iehouah</hi> by his weake crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, maketh to ſtoope the moſt puiſſant in his owne conceite. Some part of this old pallace is yet ſtanding, as S. <hi>Stephens chappel,</hi> and other buildings vpon the <hi>Thamys,</hi> neere vnto which is a moſt famous hall, called <hi>Westminſter hall,</hi> which was ſo called for that it was <hi>Aularegis,</hi> a kings court, but as touching the founder is great varietie.</p>
                     <p>Some affirme that WILLIAM RVFVS builded it:<note place="margin">E. S. de. reb. Br.</note> but M. <hi>Camden</hi> affirmeth that <hi>Hoc quod nunc habemus pretorim</hi> RIC. 2. <hi>diru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vetustiori extruxit ſuaeque habitationi dicauit.</hi> RIC. 2. built it and made it his manſion houſe. But me thinks it is to be gathered by the words of <hi>Thomas Walſingham,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Tho. Walſ.</hi> hist. Aug.</note> that <hi>Westminster hall</hi> was in the time of EDW. the 2. where he ſaith, <hi>Si ipſi Barones cum ſuis aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatoribus in aula Westmonasterii &amp; pleno parliamento venirent &amp;c.</hi> whereby it appeereth that <hi>Westminster hall</hi> and the place of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament there, was 64. yeeres before RIC. 2. But ſome may ſay, that the great Hall that nowe is,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Tho. Walſ.</hi> Ypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digni. New. pag. <hi>49.</hi>
                        </note> was not in thoſe daies, but the Hall that is nowe called <hi>White hall,</hi> where the Court of of <hi>Requests</hi> is now kept. To anſwere that the ſame <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rex</hi> E. 1. <hi>Celebrauit penticoſtes in aula magna apud Westmonasterium,</hi> whereby he maketh a diſtinction betweene thoſe two hals, for the <hi>White hall</hi> was called alſo <hi>Aula parva,</hi> the little hall: which two hals and other buildings thereunto adioining, were vſed by RIC.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13561:33"/>the 2. who cauſed all controuerſies there to be heard, (who as all other kings) in thoſe daies ſat in iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Kings</hi> ſat in Court to heare and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine cauſes.</note> &amp; wherſoeuer the king was in perſon, there was the place of hearing, and determining cauſes: ſauing that the common plees were by HEN. 3. appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be heard in a place certaine, as appeereth in <hi>magna Charta,</hi> where it is ſaide, <hi>Communia placita non ſequntur Curiam nostram. Sed teneantur in aliquo loco certo.</hi> But at this day all cauſes of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer nature, for the moſt part are heard and determinable, at this place as a place certeine.<note place="margin">S. Stephens <hi>chappelli</hi>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Betweene <hi>Westminster hall,</hi> and the <hi>Thamys</hi> is a chapple of S. <hi>Stephens:</hi> ſometime verie beautifull, though now in the outwarde ſhewe ſomething defaced: It was reedefied and augmented by EDW. 3. when he came victor out of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> about the yeere of Chriſt 1347.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Westminster</hi> had ſometime a houſe of monkes, who were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued thence by HEN. 7. and a Deane with certaine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends eſtabliſhed.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> a Buſhops ſea.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the time of EDWARD 6. it was made a biſhops See, but ſhortlie after it came againe to a Deane and Prebends; Againe Queene MARIE ordeined there an Abbot and his munkes, who continued not manie yeeres, but were againe cut off by acte of Parleament: Laſtly our moſt gratious Queene ELIZABETH made it a collegiate Church: inſtituting a Deane, twelue Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends, twelue well deſeruing ſoldiers, and fortie ſchollers: who are thereby termed <hi>The Queenes ſchollers,</hi> who, as they become woorthie, are preferred to the Vniuerſities. All which pupils, as long as they continue in this colledge, are vnder the Deane, now D. <hi>Goodman.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Alex. Neuell. Norwic.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Alexander Neuell Norwic.</hi> affirmeth that the Biſhops of <hi>Caun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie,</hi> in the time of RIC. the 1. did make their moſt abode at <hi>Westminster,</hi> as they do nowe at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> or <hi>Lomehith,</hi> and had ouer againſt the ſchoole that nowe is, a ſtately houſe:<note place="margin">Lelande.</note> yet <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande</hi> affirmeth the contrary, who ſaith, that the Biſhops of <hi>Caunterburie</hi> haue continued at <hi>Lambeth</hi> ſince the <hi>Normanes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into this land.</p>
                     <p>There is an auncient monument within the libertie of <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Charing croſſe.</note> called <hi>Charing croſſe,</hi> erected about the yeere of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Tho. Walſ.</note>1290. by EDW. 1. in memoriall of the death of <hi>Elineor</hi> his Queene, who died at <hi>Hardlie</hi> neere <hi>Lincolne,</hi> &amp; was buried in <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The libertie of <hi>Westminster</hi> extendeth to <hi>Temple bar:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Temple bar.</note> ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called of the <hi>Temple</hi> within the ſame bar, and is called the bar for that it ſtoppeth and barreth the Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> as alſo the Magiſtrates of <hi>Westminster,</hi> that neither intrude vpon other. This bar or gate was throwne downe by the Kentiſh rebels, in the time of RIC. 2.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:13561:34"/>Within the libertie of <hi>Westminster</hi> are fower pariſh Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,<note place="margin">Pariſh Churches in the libertie of <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
                        </note> beſides S. <hi>Peters,</hi> namelie,</p>
                     <p>S. <hi>Margarets</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>S. <hi>Martynes</hi> neere <hi>Charing croſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Sauoy</hi> Church.</p>
                     <p>S. <hi>Clements,</hi> called Saint <hi>Clements Dacorum,</hi> or Saint <hi>Clements Danes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the time of ſuperſtition there was in <hi>Westminster,</hi> a place called the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The Sanctuary.</note> of an old Moſaical ryte, vſed among the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi> among whom euery tribe had certaine cities, and places of refuge, to which malefactors might repaire, and for a time be protected from the rigor of the law.</p>
                     <p>There was at <hi>Westminster</hi> kept a ſtaple of wooll,<note place="margin">The Woulſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> and is at this daie, called the <hi>Woolstaple,</hi> eſtabliſhed in the time of EDWARD the 3.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Sauoye</hi> was firſt built (as M. <hi>Stowe</hi> hath recorde) by <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> Earle of <hi>Sauoy,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The Sauoy.</note> who was after made Earle of <hi>Richmonde,</hi> by HENRIE the 3. who called it the <hi>Sauoy</hi> after his Countrie. But <hi>Poll. Virg.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pollid. Virg.</note> alloweth him not Earle of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> but calleth him <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus ſebaudienſis: Peter a Sauoyan,</hi> or of the countrie of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> who as the ſame <hi>Poll.</hi> affirmeth, buylt the ſame, and called it the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoy,</hi> of his natiue Countrey <hi>Sauoye.</hi> It was belonging vnto the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> in the time of RIC. the 2. in whoſe time it was waſted, burned, and ſpoyled by the Kentiſh rebels, about the yere 1381. It was reedefied by HEN. 7. by whoſe laſt will, it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be finiſhed, and made an Hoſpitall, for the reliefe of a 100. poore people, which was perfourmed by the moſt famous HEN. the 8. his ſonne, and ſufficiently furniſhed with lande, and reuenues, for the maintenance thereof.</p>
                     <p>Queene ELIZABETH hath within the precincts of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie three faire and pleaſant pallaces:<note place="margin">Howſes of Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
                        </note> namely <hi>White hall,</hi> begun by <hi>Cardinall Woolſey,</hi> and finiſhed, with manie moſt princely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, by HEN. 8. S. <hi>Ieames,</hi> erected by the ſame king HEN. 8. and <hi>Somerſet</hi> houſe builded by the Duke of <hi>Somerſet</hi> about the yeere of Chriſt 1549.</p>
                     <p>There are other houſes worthy to be remembred within this libertie of <hi>Westminster</hi> as Burghley houſe,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Burgley</hi> houſe.</note> founded and erected by the right honorable S. <hi>William Cycell</hi> knight, Lord <hi>Burghley,</hi> Lord high treaſoror of England.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Durham</hi> or <hi>Dunelme</hi> houſe ſometime belonging to the Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Durham</hi> houſe builded.</note> it was builded by one <hi>Anthony Becke</hi> in the time of RICHARD the third. Other famous houſes of nobility are in this precinct, which to mention I omit for breuitie.</p>
                     <list>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:13561:34"/>
                        <head>Places diſtinguiſhed in the Map of Weſtminſter by theſe letters and figures following.</head>
                        <item>A. The Abbey.</item>
                        <item>B. Weſtminſter hall.</item>
                        <item>D. Long ditche.</item>
                        <item>E. Theuing lane.</item>
                        <item>F. The Amnerie.</item>
                        <item>G. The way to Toothill fielde.</item>
                        <item>H. The Lord <hi>Dacres.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>I. Lord <hi>Grayes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>K. Kings ſtreete.</item>
                        <item>L. Round Woulſtaple.</item>
                        <item>M. The Parke lodgings.</item>
                        <item>N. The Tilt-yard.</item>
                        <item>O. S. Martynes in the field.</item>
                        <item>P. Clements Inne.</item>
                        <item>Q. New Inne.</item>
                        <item>R. S. Clements Danes.</item>
                        <item>S. Temple barre.</item>
                        <item>V. Drurie lane.</item>
                        <item>Y. The Gatehouſe.</item>
                        <item>2. S. Margarets.</item>
                        <item>3. S. Stephens alley.</item>
                        <item>5. Petite Fraunce.</item>
                        <item>6. H. 7. Chappell.</item>
                        <item>7. Deanes yarde.</item>
                        <item>8. Tennies Courtes.</item>
                        <item>9. Way to Hounſlow.</item>
                        <item>10. The Powder houſe.</item>
                        <item>11. White hall Orchard.</item>
                        <item>12. The Queenes Garden.</item>
                        <item>13. Staple Inne.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>This Citie of <hi>Westminſter</hi> is knowne to haue no generall trade whereby releefe might be adminiſtred vnto the common ſort, as by Marchandize, clothing, or ſuch like, whereby the common wealth of a Citie is maineteined, and the inferiour people ſet to worke, had they not therefore ſome other meanes, the common ſort could nor be ſuſteined.<note place="margin">The chiefe meane whereby Weſtminſter is releeued.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The firſt and principall meane whereby they are releeued, is hir Maieſties reſidence at <hi>White hall,</hi> or S. <hi>Ieames,</hi> whence if hir
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13561:35"/>grace be long abſent, the poore people forthwith complaine of penury and want, of a hard and miſerable world. And therefore doe the people in manner generally ſeeme to power forth dayly petitions, that it might pleaſe God to draw hir Maieſtie to be reſident at one of theſe places, whereat they reioyce and fare long the better. The like deſire of hir Royall preſence haue other places, where hir Maieſties Pallaces are placed. And hir Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie in gracious conſideration of their eſtates, doth viſit them as it were <hi>Alternis vicebus,</hi> by turne at hir highnes pleaſure, more for the comfort and releefe of the poore people, then for hir owne priuate delight. Therefore yee Citizens of <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> and other, whatſoeuer, forget not to be thankefull to the the Almightie for hir Royall preſence, hartely praying the King of Kings, to maintaine hir a proſpering Queene long and many yeeres, and euery faithfull hart will ioyne with you, hauing alſo the benefite of hir bleſſed inclination.</p>
                     <p>The ſeconde meane whereby this poore Citie is maintained,<note place="margin">The ſecond meane, the Tearmes.</note> and the people releeued, is by the fower Termes in the yeere, for it hath pleaſed God to eſtabliſh there, the place where Iuſtice, lawe, and euerie mans right is (God graunt it) with equall bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, indifferently adminiſtred: whereunto great multitudes of people, vſually flocke, whoſe reſort although the Citie enioie but in the forenoone, yet yeeldeth their preſence, manie pence to the poore towne.</p>
                     <p>There was in the time of EDW. 1. a diſcontinuance of the lawe,<note place="margin">The hearing of cauſes remooued to <hi>Yorke.</hi>
                        </note> in this Citie, and was thence remooued to <hi>Yorke,</hi> where it continued, ſeauen yeeres after reduced to the former place. It hath beene often diſcontinued by the disfauour of Princes, and their conceiued diſpleaſure againſt the inhabitants of the place, for diſobedience, as a generall puniſhment. Receiue this ye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Westminster,</hi> as a neceſſarie premonition, that ye reſt carefull and vigilant, leaſt the king of kings mooue her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie to place the determination of cauſes elſe where, which now is vnto you no ſmall ſupport.</p>
                     <p>The third and laſt meane (though it come ſeldome) is that great and generall convencion of all the eſtates of this lande,<note place="margin">The third mean, the Parliament.</note> the high Court of Parleament, which draweth vnto it a great acceſſe of noble perſons, and others, to the place of aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie, which is alſo ſet moſt gratiouſly within this Citie, which yeeldeth no ſmall releefe vnto the ſame, which alſo (as is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in hiſtories) hath beene holden at diuers other places in this land.</p>
                     <p>It is not yet forgotten,<note place="margin">The tearme re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued to Hertford.</note> no doubt, how the God offended, viſited not onely this Citie, but alſo <hi>London,</hi> with a dangerous late infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, inſomuch as the laſt <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Terme was remooued to
<pb facs="tcp:13561:35"/>
                        <hi>Hertforde</hi> caſtle, which pinched the poore, and made the rich to complaine, in both theſe Cities: yet a more gentle forewarning of his diſpleaſure he cannot ſhew, who longing for new obedience in vs, calleth vs by diuers meanes, and without ſpeedie and harty repentance we ſhall likewiſe periſh.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="list_of_roads">
               <head>The principal high waies from London through <hi>Middleſex,</hi> and towards what eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall places in England they lead.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>THe way noted with this figure 2. leadeth to Stanes, &amp; thence towards Sarisburie, Exeter and other places in the weſt.</item>
                  <item>3. Leadeth to Colnebrooke, towardes Windſore, Reading, Bath, Briſtow, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>4. To Vxbridge, and ſo towardes Oxford, Glouceſter, &amp; ſouth Wales.</item>
                  <item>5. To Egewoorth, towards Woodſtocke, Buckingham, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke, Stafford, Worceſter, Cheſter, and north Wales.</item>
                  <item>6. To S. Albans, towards Bedford, Northampton, Leiceſter, Darby, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>7. Towardes Waltham, Hartforde, Bedforde, Huntingdon, Cambridge, into Norfolke: towardes Lincolne, Yorke and the Northen parts.</item>
                  <item>9. To Stratford on the Bow, and ſo into Eſſex and Suffolke.</item>
                  <item>10. Leadeth into Surrey and Suſſex.</item>
                  <item>11. To Kingſton vpon Thamis, Guyldford, Farneham, Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter, Arrondell, Chechiſter, Southampton, Porteſmouth, &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="list_of_residents">
               <head>Noblemen, and Gentlemen, for the moſt part, hauing houſes, or reſidence, within this Shire.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>A.</head>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Ed. Anderſon,</hi> Lord chiefe iuſtice of the common plees pag. 21.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>George Aſhbie.</hi> pag. 16.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>George Atee.</hi> pag. 17.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>George Alleley</hi> at <hi>Daleſon hill.</hi> pag. 18.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>B.</head>
                  <item>L. <hi>Burghley,</hi> L. High Treaſurer of England. pag. 38.</item>
                  <item>L. <hi>Barnes.</hi> pag. 37.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Burrowes</hi> at lyme houſe. pag. 36.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Bellamy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Buſhop of <hi>London.</hi> pag. 20.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>C.</head>
                  <item>L. <hi>Compion</hi> pag. 37. 41.</item>
                  <item>L. <hi>Corbet.</hi> pag. 21.</item>
                  <item>L. <hi>Cornewell.</hi> pag. 18.</item>
                  <item>L. <hi>Cockeram</hi> at Hamſted. pag. 22</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Cunſtable</hi> at old Ford. pag. 37.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Cornewallies.</hi> pag. 22.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Carle</hi> at Maribone park.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>D.</head>
                  <item>E. of <hi>Darby</hi> at Iſtleworth. pag. 17.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:13561:36"/>L. <hi>Dacres.</hi> pag. 17. 18. 23.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>F.</head>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Iohn Forteſcue</hi> knight, one of hir Maieſt priuy counſel pag. 21.</item>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Fleetewood.</hi> pag. 19.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>G.</head>
                  <item>ladie <hi>Greſham.</hi> pag. 37.</item>
                  <item>ladie <hi>Gylman</hi> at Twickenham pag. 41</item>
                  <item>ladie <hi>Gomerſhall,</hi> pag. 16.</item>
                  <item>ladie <hi>Gifford.</hi> pag. 37.</item>
                  <item>ladie <hi>Goddarde</hi> at Tottenham perſonage. pag. 41.</item>
                  <item>ladie <hi>Gerrard.</hi> pag. 223.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>H.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ierome Halley.</hi> pag. 17.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Hatrey,</hi> at Riſelyp. pag. 38.</item>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Rowlande Haywarde</hi> knight at Clapton. pag. 17.</item>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Huggines</hi> at Meerſtreet. pag. 37.</item>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Io. Harrington</hi> at Stepney. pag. 39.</item>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Hare</hi> at Pymmes. pag. 38.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>K.</head>
                  <item>auditor <hi>King</hi> neer Finchley. pag. 20.</item>
                  <item>alderma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Kempton</hi> at Hadley pag. 21.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thom. Kneuet</hi> at S. Iames parke</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>L.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Lyons.</hi> pag. 41.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Leeke.</hi> pag. 41.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Lacye.</hi> pag. 18.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>M.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Middlemore.</hi> pag. 19.</item>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Richard Martyn</hi> knight neere Tottenham.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>N.</head>
                  <item>L. <hi>North.</hi> pag. 22.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>George Nicholſon</hi> at Twicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham. pag. 41.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>O.</head>
                  <item>earle of <hi>Oxforde.</hi> pag. 37.</item>
                  <item>alderman <hi>Offley</hi> at Clapton. pag. 17.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>P.</head>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Iohn Popham</hi> knight, Lorde chiefe Iuſtice of England. pag. 20.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ric. Peacocke,</hi> at Northend. pag. 37.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ric. Plumbe</hi> at Northende by Fulham.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ric. Paine</hi> at Harlſtone green. pag. 23.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ric. Payne</hi> neer Harneſey. pag. 21.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Q.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ric. Quynnye</hi> at Chalcot, or Chalkhill. pag. 17.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>R.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ric. Roane.</hi> pag. 25.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ric. Ryth</hi> at Twickenham. pag. 41.</item>
                  <item>alderman <hi>Roe.</hi> pag. 36.</item>
                  <item>alderman <hi>Ryder</hi> at Stepney. pag. 39.</item>
                  <item>ladie <hi>Iſabell</hi> Counties of Rut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land at Steyney. pag. 39</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>S.</head>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Thomas Sherley.</hi> pag. 39.</item>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Sewell</hi> at Cannons. pag. 17.</item>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Skenington</hi> neere Harneſey pag. 21.</item>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Skeuington.</hi> pag. 17.</item>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Sadler</hi> ad Edmonton. pag. 18.</item>
                  <item>ſir doctor <hi>Seyſar</hi> neere Tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenham.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>T.</head>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Trott.</hi> pag. 17.</item>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Throgmorton</hi> at Stepney pag. 39.</item>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Thomſon</hi> at Lalam. pag. 36.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <item>ſir <hi>Vaghan</hi> at Littleton. pag. 36.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>W.</head>
                  <item>L. <hi>Wentworth.</hi> pag. 17.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Walliſon,</hi> at Riſelipe. pag. 38.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Wroth.</hi> pag. 17. &amp; 37.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Waade.</hi> pag. 16.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Weeks</hi> at Hamſteed. pag. 22.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <p>I craue patience though I haue not giuen to euerie man his addition of <hi>Eſquire</hi> or <hi>Gent.</hi> for that I may eaſely erre there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, without the eſpeciall aide of an expert Herault.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:36"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the right worſhipful M. WILLIAM WAADE</hi> Eſquire, one of the clearks of hir Maiesties moſt Honorable priuie Counſell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, I cannot reſt vnreadie in deſire, to yeeld requitall of your aide extended towards the publication of this firſt part of my SPECVLVM BRITANNIAE: wherin I muſt, and do thankfullie acknowledge your good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination not towards me onely, but to all ſuch as indeuour mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters tending to publike good. In lieu therfore of a farther faithful recompence, accept, I beſeech you, my willing indeuor, vntil time afforde ablenes to make better repay.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>In magnis &amp; voluiſſe dat eſt,</hi> I. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>A I Lettori.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>HAſpeſo molti di per Amor vostro.</l>
               <l>A pinger queste carte famigliare,</l>
               <l>Citte, castelli, fiume deliniare,</l>
               <l>Le terre miſurar Nordeno nostro</l>
               <l>Non guardate à le carte, ne à l'inchioſtro</l>
               <l>Perche è vna coſa, che non ſa parlare</l>
               <l>Guardate pur ſe l'opra vi può entrare</l>
               <l>Se'l ſpecchio ui piace, che vimostro</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Non otiòſa mà faticoſa impreſa</l>
               <l>è questo ſpecchio del Britanno lido.</l>
               <l>Non è composto ſenza molta ſpeſa</l>
               <l>Non cercano tal' opr' alcuno nido.</l>
               <l>Norden il ſpecchio tuo ſenza conteſa</l>
               <l>Riſplenderà dou'è più chiaro il grido.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ar. Oln.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>Ingenuo lectori, de opere, &amp; <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thore te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rastichon.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>QVem tulit is punctum, qui miſcuit vtile dulci;</l>
            <l>Nordenus tulit hunc, vtile, dulce canens.</l>
            <l>Vtile, dulce canit, digni laude ille, liberque:</l>
            <l>Nam placet, &amp; prodeſt, vtile, dulce, canens.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Notitia nobile nomen:</hi> Robertus Nicolſonus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:37"/>
            <head>Sur le Miroir de grand Bretaigne, de <hi>M. Ichan Norden.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>GArdez gentils, regardez cest' ouurage,</l>
            <l>Treſ-doctes Dames, &amp; treſ-ſages, Sieurs:</l>
            <l>Moult delectant voz yeulx, voz ſens, &amp; coeurs,</l>
            <l>Cy fait Plaiſir, auec Profit mariage.</l>
            <l>Chacun Degre, rumine, chachun Aage,</l>
            <l>Ce petit liure, plein de grands doulceurs:</l>
            <l>Rend luy louange, qui doulces rend odeurs,</l>
            <l>Que chacun fait, qui eſt ſçedil;auant ou ſage.</l>
            <l>Les autres ſont autheurs d' Enui', &amp; vice,</l>
            <l>Ennemis a vertu, ſciens, &amp; Notice,</l>
            <l>Vilipendans les oeuures de ſçedil;auoir:</l>
            <l>Mais nobles, doctes, &amp; gentils eſprits,</l>
            <l>Qui compte tiennent des elegans eſcripts,</l>
            <l>Hault priſeront NORDEN ſon cler Miroir.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>N'ayant eſpour qu' en Dieu. <hi>Robert Nicolſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Corrections.</head>
            <list>
               <item>In pag. 11. line 5. for <hi>eighteene,</hi> read <hi>thirteene.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In pag. 21. for <hi>Io. Forteſcue</hi> eſquire, read ſir <hi>Iohn Forteſcue</hi> knight.</item>
               <item>In pag 27. for 5191. read 3911.</item>
               <item>In the ſame pag. for <hi>Antonius,</hi> read <hi>Antoninus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In pag. 47. for <hi>Staple Inne,</hi> read <hi>Lyons Inne.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:37"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:38"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:38"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:39"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:39"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:40"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:40"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:41"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:41"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:42"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:42"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:43"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13561:43"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:13561:44"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:13561:44"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:13561:45"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13561:45"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:13561:46"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:13561:46"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:13561:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:47"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:48"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:48"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:49"/>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:13561:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:13561:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:13561:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:13561:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:13561:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:13561:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:13561:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:13561:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:13561:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:13561:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13561:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:13561:55"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:13561:55"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:13561:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:13561:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13561:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:13561:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:13561:58"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:58"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:59"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:60"/>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:13561:60"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:13561:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:13561:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:13561:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:13561:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:13561:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:13561:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:13561:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:13561:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:13561:65"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:13561:65"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:13561:66"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:13561:66"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:13561:67"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:13561:67"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:13561:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:13561:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:13561:69"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:13561:69"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:13561:70"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:70"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:71"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:71"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:72"/>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:13561:72"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:13561:73"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:73"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:74"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13561:74"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
